<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<section  xml:id="Numbers-and-Operations"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"><title>Numbers and Operations</title>
<subsection xml:id="Order-of-Operations"><title>Order of Operations</title>

<p>Numerical calculations often involve more than one operation. So that everyone agrees on how such expressions should be evaluated, we follow the <term>order of operations</term>.</p>

<assemblage><title>Order of Operations</title>
<p><ol label="1">
        <li><p>Simplify any expressions within grouping symbols (parentheses, brackets, square root bars, or fraction bars). Start with the innermost grouping symbols and work outward.</p></li>
        <li><p>Evaluate all powers and roots.</p></li>
        <li><p>Perform multiplications and divisions in order from left to right.</p></li>
        <li><p>Perform additions and subtractions in order from left to right.</p></li>
    </ol></p></assemblage>
</subsection>

<subsection><title>Parentheses and Fraction Bars</title>

<p>We can use parentheses to override the multiplication-first rule. Compare the two expressions below.
    <md>
        <mrow>\amp\text{The sum of 4 times 6 and 10} \amp\amp \alert{4 \cdot 6} + 10</mrow>
        <mrow>\amp\text{4 times the sum of 6 and 10} \amp\amp  4(\alert{6 + 10})</mrow>
    </md></p>
<p>In the first expression, we perform the multiplication <m>4\times 6</m> first, but in the second expression we perform the addition <m>6 + 10</m> first, because it is enclosed in parentheses.</p>
<p>The location (or absence) of parentheses can drastically alter the meaning of an expression. In the following example, note how the location of the parentheses changes the value of the expression.</p>

<example xml:id="example-parentheses"><p><ol label="a">
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}[t]5-3\cdot \alert{4^2} \amp = 5-3\cdot 16\\
                \amp = 5-48=-43
                \end{aligned} </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}[t]5-(\alert{3\cdot 4})^2 \amp = 5-12^2\\
                \amp= 5-144 = -139
                 \end{aligned}</m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}[t](5-\alert{3\cdot 4})^2 \amp = (5-12)^2\\
                \amp = (-7)^2 = 49
                \end{aligned}</m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}[t](\alert{5-3})\cdot 4^2 \amp = 2\cdot 4^2\\
                \amp = 2\cdot 16 = 32
                \end{aligned}</m></p></li>
        </ol></p></example>

<warning><p>In the expression <m>5 - 12^2</m>, which appears in <xref ref="example-parentheses" text="type-global"/>, the exponent <m>2</m> applies only to <m>12</m>, not to <m>-12</m>. Thus, <m>5 - 12^2 \ne 5 + 144</m>.</p></warning>

<p>The order of operations mentions other grouping devices besides parentheses: fraction bars and square root bars. Notice how the placement of the fraction bar affects the expressions in the next example.</p>

<example><p><ol label="a" cols="2">
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}[t]
                \frac{1+2}{3\cdot 4} \amp = \frac{3}{12}\\
                \amp = \frac{1}{4}
                \end{aligned}</m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}[t]
                1+\frac{2}{3\cdot 4} \amp = 1+ \frac{2}{12}\\
                \amp = 1+\frac{1}{6}=\frac{7}{6}
                \end{aligned}                </m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}[t]
                \frac{1+2}{3}\cdot 4 \amp = \frac{3}{3}\cdot 4\\
                \amp = 1\cdot 4=4
                \end{aligned}</m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}[t]
                1+\frac{2}{3}\cdot 4 \amp = 1+ \frac{8}{3}\\
                \amp = \frac{3}{3}+\frac{8}{3}=\frac{11}{3}
                \end{aligned}                </m></p></li>
        </ol></p></example>
</subsection>

<subsection><title>Radicals</title>

<p>You are already familiar with square roots. Every nonnegative number has two square roots, defined as follows:
    <me>\blert{s ~~\text{ is a square root of }~~ n ~~\text{ if }~~s^2 = n}</me>
There are several other kinds of roots, one of which is called the <term>cube root</term><idx>cube root</idx>, denoted by <m>\sqrt[3]{n}</m>. We define the cube root as follows.</p>

<assemblage><title>Cube Roots</title><idx>cube root</idx><p>
    <me>b ~~\text{ is a cube root of }~~~ n ~~~\text{ if }~~~ b ~\text{ cubed equals }~~n.</me>
    In symbols, we write
    <me>\blert{b=\sqrt[3]{n} ~~\text{ if } ~~ b^3=n}</me>
</p></assemblage>

<note><p>Although we cannot take the square root of a <em>negative number</em>, we can take the <em>cube root</em> of <em>any</em> real number. For example,
    <me>\sqrt[3]{64}=4 ~~\text{ because }~~ 4^3=64</me>
and
    <me>\sqrt[3]{-27}=-3 ~~\text{ because }~~ (-3)^3=-27</me></p></note>

<p>In the order of operations, simplifying radicals and powers comes after parentheses but before products and quotients.</p>

<example><statement><p>Simplify each expression.<ol label="a" cols="3">
            <li><m>3\sqrt[3]{-8}</m></li>
            <li><m>2-\sqrt[3]{-125}</m></li>
            <li><m>\displaystyle{\frac{6-\sqrt[3]{-27}}{2}}</m></li>
        </ol></p></statement>
<solution><p>
<ol label="a">
            <li><m>3\sqrt[3]{-8}=3(-2)=-6</m></li>
            <li><m>2-\sqrt[3]{-125}=2-(-5)=7</m></li>
            <li><m>\displaystyle{\frac{6-\sqrt[3]{-27}}{2}=\frac{6-(-3)}{2}=\frac{9}{2}}</m></li>
        </ol></p></solution></example>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="Scientific-Notation"><title>Scientific Notation</title>

<p>Scientists and engineers regularly encounter very large numbers such as
    <me>5,980,000,000,000,000,000,000,000</me>
(the mass of the Earth in kilograms) and very small numbers such as
    <me>0.000 \,000 \,000 \,000 \,000 \,000 \,000 \,001 \,67</me>
(the mass of a hydrogen atom in grams). These numbers can be written in a more compact and useful form by using powers of <m>10</m>.</p>
<p>In our base <m>10</m> number system, multiplying a number by a positive power of <m>10</m> has the effect of moving the decimal place <m>k</m> places to the right, where <m>k</m> is the exponent in the power of <m>10</m>. For example,
    <me>3\alert{.}529 \times 10^\alert{2} = 352\alert{.}9 ~~~\text{ and }~~~ 25 \times 10^4 = 250,000</me>
 Multiplying by a power of <m>10</m> with a negative exponent moves the decimal place to the left. For example,
    <me>1728 \times 10^{-3} = 1.728 ~~~\text{ and }~~~ 4.6 \times 10^{-5} = 0.000046</me></p>
<p>Using this property, we can write any number as the product of a number between <m>1</m> and <m>10</m> (including <m>1</m>) and a power of <m>10</m>. For example, the mass of the Earth and the mass of a hydrogen atom can be expressed as
    <me>5.98 \times 1024 \text{ kilograms}\hphantom{blank} \text{ and }\hphantom{blank}1.67 \times 10^{-24} \text{ gram}</me>
respectively. A number written in this form is said to be expressed in <term>scientific notation</term><idx>scientific notation</idx>.</p>

<assemblage><title>To Write a Number in Scientific Notation:</title>
<p><ol label="1">
        <li><p>
            Locate the decimal point so that there is exactly one nonzero digit to its left.</p></li>
        <li><p>
            Count the number of places you moved the decimal point: This determines the power of <m>10</m>.
            <ol label="a">
                <li><p>
                    If the original number is greater than <m>10</m>, the exponent is positive.</p></li>
                <li><p>
                    If the original number is less than <m>1</m>, the exponent is negative.</p></li>
            </ol></p></li>
    </ol></p></assemblage>

<example><p>Write each number in scientific notation.<ol label="a">
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}[t]
                478,000 \amp = 4.78000 \times 10^5 \amp \amp \blert{\text{Move the decimal 5 places.}}\\
                \amp = 4.78 \times 10^5
                \end{aligned}</m></p></li>
            <li><p><m>
                \begin{aligned}[t]
                0.00032 \amp= 00003.2 \times 10^{-4} \amp \amp \blert{\text{Move the decimal 4 places.}}\\
                \amp = 3.2 \times 10^{-4}
                \end{aligned}</m></p></li>
        </ol></p></example>

<example><statement><p>The average American eats <m>110</m> kilograms of meat per year. It takes about <m>16</m> kilograms of grain to produce <m>1</m> kilogram of meat, and advanced farming techniques can produce about <m>6000</m> kilograms of grain on each hectare of arable land. (The hectare is <m>10,000</m> square meters, or just under <m>2 \frac{1}{2}</m> acres.) Now, the total land area of the Earth is about <m>13</m> billion hectares, but only about <m>11\%</m> of that land is arable. Is it possible for each of the <m>7.6</m> billion people on Earth to eat as much meat as Americans do?</p></statement>

<solution><p>First we will compute the amount of meat necessary to feed every person on Earth <m>110</m> kilograms per year. In 2018 there are <m>7.6 \times 10^9</m> people on Earth.
        <me>(5.5\times 10^9 \text{ people})\times (110 \text{ kg/person}) = 8.36 \times 10^{11} \text{ kg of meat}</me>
Next we will compute the amount of grain needed to produce that much meat.
        <me>(16 \text{ kg of grain/kg of meat})\times (8.36 \times 10^{11} \text{ kg of meat}) = 1.34 \times 10^{13} \text{ kg of grain}</me>
Next we will see how many hectares of land are needed to produce that much grain.
        <me>(1.34\times 10^{13} \text{ kg of grain})\div(6000 \text{ kg/hectare}) = 2.23\times 10^{11} \text{ hectares}</me>
Finally, we will compute the amount of arable land available for grain production.
        <me>0.11\times (13\times 10^9 \text{ hectares}) = 1.43\times 10^9 \text{ hectares}</me>
Thus, even if we use every hectare of arable land to produce grain for livestock, we will not have enough to provide every person on Earth with <m>110</m> kilograms of meat per year.</p></solution></example>
</subsection>

<xi:include href="./summary-A-1.xml" /> <!-- summary  -->
<xi:include href="./section-A-1-exercises.xml" /> <!-- exercises  -->

</section>