<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<section xml:id="appendix-Linear-Systems-in-Two-Variables" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ><title>Linear Systems in Two Variables</title><idx>linear system</idx><introduction>
<p>A <m>2\times 2</m> <term>system</term> of equations is a set of <m>2</m> equations in the same <m>2</m> variables. A <term>solution</term><idx>solution</idx> of a <m>2\times 2</m> system is an ordered pair that makes each equation in the system true. In this section, we review two algebraic methods for solving <m>2\times 2</m> linear systems: substitution and elimination.</p></introduction>

<subsection><title>Solving Systems by Substitution</title>

<p>The basic strategy for the <term>substitution</term><idx>substitution</idx> method can be described as follows.</p>

<assemblage><title>Steps for Solving a <m>2\times 2</m> System by Substitution</title>
<p><ol label="1">
    <li><p>Solve one of the equations for one of the variables in terms of the other.</p></li>
    <li><p>Substitute this expression into the second equation; doing so yields an equation in one variable.</p></li>
    <li><p>Solve the new equation.</p></li>
    <li><p>Use the result of step 1 to find the other variable.</p></li>
</ol></p></assemblage>

<example><statement><p>Staci stocks two kinds of sleeping bags in her sporting goods store, a standard model and a down-filled model for colder temperatures. From past experience, she estimates that she will sell twice as many of the standard variety as of the down filled. She has room to stock 60 sleeping bags at a time. How many of each variety should Staci order?</p></statement>
<solution><p><ol>
    <li><p>
        <md><mrow>\amp\text{Number of standard sleeping bags: }~x</mrow>
            <mrow>\amp\text{Number of down-filled sleeping bags: }~y</mrow></md></p></li>
    <li><p>Write two equations about the variables. Staci needs twice as many standard model as down filled, so
                <md><mrow>x \amp = 2y\amp\amp\hphantom{blankety}(1)</mrow></md>
        Also, the total number of sleeping bags is 60, so
                <md><mrow>x+y \amp = 60\amp\amp\hphantom{blank}(2)</mrow></md></p></li>
    <li><p>We will solve this system using substitution. Notice that Equation (1) is already solved for <m>x</m> in terms of <m>y</m>: <m>x = 2y</m>. Substitute <m>\alert{2y}</m> for <m>x</m> in Equation (2) to obtain
            <md><mrow>\alert{2y} + y \amp = 60</mrow>
                <mrow>3y\amp = 60</mrow></md>
        Solving for <m>y</m>, we find <m>y=\alert{20}</m>. Finally, substitute this value into Equation (1) to find
                <me>x = 2(\alert{20}) = 40</me>
        The solution to the system is <m>x = 40, y = 20</m>.</p></li>
    <li><p>Staci should order <m>40</m> standard sleeping bags and <m>20</m> down-filled bags.</p></li>
</ol></p></solution></example>
</subsection>

<subsection><title>Solving Systems by Elimination</title>

<p>The method of substitution is convenient if one of the variables in the system has a coefficient of <m>1</m> or <m>-1</m>, because it is easy to solve for that variable. If none of the coefficients is <m>1</m> or <m>-1</m>, then a second method, called <term>elimination</term><idx>elimination</idx>, is usually more efficient.</p>

<p>The method of elimination is based on the following properties of linear equations.</p>

<assemblage><title>Properties of Linear Systems</title>
<p><ol label="1">
    <li><p>Multiplying a linear equation by a (nonzero) constant does not change its solutions. That is, any solution of the equation
            <me>ax + by = c</me>
    is also a solution of the equation
            <me>kax + kby = kc</me></p></li>
    <li><p>Adding (or subtracting) two linear equations does not change their common solutions. That is, any solution of the system
        <md><mrow>a_1x + b_1 y \amp = c_1</mrow>
            <mrow>a_2x + b_2 y \amp = c_2</mrow></md>
    is also a solution of the equation
            <me>(a_1 + a_2) x + (b_1 + b_2) y = c_1 + c_2</me></p></li>
    </ol></p></assemblage>

<example xml:id="example-linear-combinations"><statement><p>Solve the system by the method of elimination.
        <md alignment="alignat">
            <mrow>2x\amp {}+{}\amp 3y\amp ={}\amp 8 \hphantom{blankblank}\amp(1)</mrow>
            <mrow>3x\amp {}-{}\amp 4y\amp ={}\amp -5 \hphantom{blankblank}\amp(2)</mrow>
        </md></p></statement>
<solution><p>We first decide which variable to eliminate, <m>x</m> or <m>y</m>. We can choose whichever looks easiest. In this problem, we choose to eliminate <m>x</m>.</p>
<p> We next look for the smallest number that both coefficients, <m>2</m> and <m>3</m>, divide into evenly. This number is <m>6</m>. We want the coefficients of <m>x</m> to become <m>6</m> and <m>-6</m>, so we will multiply Equation (1) by <m>3</m> and Equation (2) by <m>-2</m> to obtain
        <md alignment="alignat">
            <mrow>6x\amp {}+{}\amp 9y\amp ={}\amp 24 \hphantom{blankblank}\amp(1\text{a})</mrow>
            <mrow>-6x\amp {}+{}\amp 8y\amp ={}\amp 10 \hphantom{blankblank}\amp(2\text{a})</mrow>
        </md>
Now we add the corresponding terms of (1a) and (2a). The <m>x</m>-terms are eliminated, yielding an equation in one variable.
        <md alignment="alignat">
            <mrow>6x\amp {}+{}\amp 9y\amp ={}\amp 24 \hphantom{blankblank}\amp(1\text{a})</mrow>
            <mrow>-6x\amp {}+{}\amp 8y\amp ={}\amp 10 \hphantom{blankblank}\amp(2\text{a})</mrow>
            <mrow>{}\amp {}{}\amp 17y\amp ={}\amp 34 \hphantom{blankblank}\amp(3)</mrow>
        </md>
We solve this equation for <m>y</m> to find <m>y=\alert{2}</m>. We can substitute this value of <m>y</m> into any of our equations involving both <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>. If we choose Equation (1), then
        <me>2x + 3 (\alert{2}) = 8</me>
and solving this equation yields <m>x=1</m>. The ordered pair <m>(1, 2)</m> is a solution to the system. You should verify that these values satisfy both original equations.</p></solution></example>

<p>We summarize the strategy for solving a linear system by elimination.</p>

<assemblage><title>Steps for Solving a <m>2\times 2</m> Linear System by Elimination</title>
<p><ol label="1">
    <li><p>Choose one of the variables to eliminate. Multiply each equation by a suitable factor so that the coefficients of that variable are opposites.</p></li>
    <li><p>Add the two new equations termwise.</p></li>
    <li><p>Solve the resulting equation for the remaining variable.</p></li>
    <li><p>Substitute the value found in step 3 into either of the original equations and solve for the other variable.</p></li>
</ol></p></assemblage>

<p>In <xref ref="example-linear-combinations" text="type-global"/>, we added <m>3</m> times the first equation to <m>-2</m> times the second equation. The result from adding a constant multiple of one equation to a constant multiple of another equation is called a <term>linear combination</term><idx>linear combination</idx> of the two equations. The method of elimination is also called the method of linear combinations<idx>linear combinations</idx>.</p>

<p>If either equation in a system has fractional coefficients, it is helpful to clear the fractions before applying the method of linear combinations.</p>

<example><statement><p>Solve the system by linear combinations.
        <md alignment="alignat">
            <mrow>\frac{2}{3}x\amp {}-{}\amp y\amp ={}\amp 2 \hphantom{blankblank}\amp(1)</mrow>
            <mrow>x\amp {}+{}\amp \frac{1}{2}y\amp ={}\amp 7 \hphantom{blankblank}\amp(2)</mrow>
        </md></p></statement>
<solution><p>Multiply each side of Equation (1) by <m>3</m> and each side of Equation (2) by <m>2</m> to clear the fractions:
        <md alignment="alignat">
            <mrow>2x\amp {}-{}\amp 3y\amp ={}\amp 6 \hphantom{blankblank}\amp(1\text{a})</mrow>
            <mrow>2x\amp {}+{}\amp y\amp ={}\amp 14 \hphantom{blankblank}\amp(2\text{a})</mrow></md>
To eliminate the variable <m>x</m>, multiply Equation (2a) by <m>-1</m> and add the result to Equation (1a) to get
        <md>
            <mrow>-4y \amp = -8 \amp\amp\blert{\text{Divide both sides by -4.}}</mrow>
            <mrow>y \amp = 2</mrow></md>
Substitute <m>\alert{2}</m> for <m>y</m> in one of the original equations and solve for <m>x</m>. We use Equation (2).
        <md>
            <mrow>x + \frac{1}{2}(\alert{2}) \amp = 7 \amp\amp\blert{\text{Subtract 1 from both sides.}}</mrow>
            <mrow>x \amp = 6</mrow></md>
        Verify that <m>x=6</m> and <m>y=2</m> satisfy both Equations (1) and (2). The solution to the system is the ordered pair <m>(6, 2)</m>.</p></solution></example>
</subsection>

<xi:include href="./summary-A-5.xml" /> <!-- summary  -->
<xi:include href="./section-A-5-exercises.xml" /> <!-- exercises  -->
</section>