<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="chap9-summary" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Chapter Summary and Review</title>
<subsection><title>Key Concepts</title>
<p><ol label="1">
	<li>A function whose inputs are a set of successive positive integers is called a sequence.</li>
	<li>The output values are called the terms of the sequence.</li>
	<li>A formula in terms of <m>n</m> for the <m>n^{\text{th}}</m> term of a sequence is called the general term of the sequence.</li>
	<li>A sequence is defined recursively if each term of the sequence is defined in terms of its predecessors.</li>
	<li>A sequence in which each term can be obtained from the previous term by adding a fixed amount is called an arithmetic sequence.</li>
	<li>The fixed amount between two successive terms of an arithmetic sequence is called the common difference.</li>  
	<li>An arithmetic sequence defines a linear function of <m>n</m>.</li>
	<li>The <m>n^{\text{th}}</m> term of an arithmetic sequence is <m>~a_n = a + (n-1)d</m>.</li>
	<li>A sequence in which each term can be obtained from the previous term by multiplying by a fixed amount is called a  geometric sequence.</li>
	<li>The ratio of two successive terms of a geometridc sequence is called the common ratio.</li>
	<li>A geometric sequence defines an exponential function of <m>n</m>.</li> 
	<li>The <m>n^{\text{th}}</m> term of a geometric sequence is <m>~a_n = ar^{n-1}</m>.</li>
	<li>The sum of the terms of a sequence is called a series.</li>
	<li>The sum <m>S_n</m> of the first <m>n</m> terms of an arithmetic sequence is
			<me>S_n = \dfrac{n}{2} (a_1 + a_n)</me></li>
	<li>The sum <m>S_n</m> of the first <m>n</m> terms of a geometric sequence is
			<me>S_n = \dfrac{a_{n+1} - a_1}{r-1}</me></li> 
	<li>We can use sigma notation to denote a series.</li>
	<li>It is possible to add infinitely many terms and arrive at a finite sum if the terms are small enough.</li>
	<li>The sum of an infinite geometric series <m>~~\displaystyle{\sum_{k=0}^{\infty} ar^{k-1}}~~</m> is
			<me>S_{\infty} = \dfrac{a}{1-r}~~~~~~\text{if}~~~~~~-1 \lt r \lt 1</me></li>    
	<li>If <m>\abs{r} \ge 1</m> in an infinite geometric series, the series does not have a sum.</li>
	<li>The binomial coefficient <m>~_nC_k~</m> is the coefficient of the term containing <m>b^k</m> in the expansion of <m>(a+b)^n</m>.</li>
	<li>The numbers in Pascal's triangle are the binomial coefficients. Specifically, the number in the <m>k^{\text{th}}</m> position (starting with <m>k=0</m>) of the <m>n^{\text{th}}</m> row of the triangle is <m>~_nC_k~</m>.</li>
	<li>If <m>n</m> is a positive integer,
			<me>n! = n \cdot (n-1) \cdot (n-2) \cdot \cdots \cdot 3\cdot 2 \cdot 1</me></li>
	<li>For <m>n \ge 0</m> and <m>0 \le k \le n</m>,
			<me>~_nC_k~ = \dfrac{n!}{(n-k)!~k!}</me></li> 
	<li>The Binomial Theorem
			<me>(a+b)^n = ~~\displaystyle{\sum_{k=0}^{n} ~_nC_k~ a^{n-k}b^k}</me></li></ol></p>
</subsection>
<!-- <subsubsection> -->
	<xi:include href="./chap9-rev-problems.xml" />   <!-- exercises  -->
<!-- </subsubsection> -->

</section>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->