<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="chap10-summary" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Chapter Summary and Review</title>
<subsection><title>Key Concepts</title>
<p><ol label="1">
	<li>The most general form of a second-degree equation in two variables is 
        <me>Ax^2 + Bxy + Cy^2 + Dx + Ey + F = 0</me>
    where <m>A, B</m>, and <m>C</m> cannot all be zero, and its graph is a conic section.</li>
	<li>An ellipse is the set of points in the plane the sum of whose distances from two fixed points (called the foci) is a constant.</li>
	<li>The standard form for an ellipse centered at the origin is
			<me>\dfrac{x^2}{a^2} + \dfrac{y^2}{b^2} = 1</me></li>
	<li>A hyperbola is the set of points in the plane, the difference of whose distances from two fixed points (the foci) is a constant.</li>
	<li>The standard form for a hyperbola centered at the origin with foci on the <m>x</m>-axis is
			<me>\dfrac{x^2}{a^2} - \dfrac{y^2}{b^2} = 1</me>
	The standard form for a hyperbola centered at the origin with foci on the <m>y</m>-axis is
		<me>\dfrac{y^2}{b^2} - \dfrac{x^2}{a^2} = 1</me></li>
	<li>We can draw the asymptotes by first forming the "central rectangle," whose sides pass through the vertices and covertices.  The asymptotes are the diagonals of this rectangle.</li>
	<li>A parabola is the set of points in the plane whose distances from a fixed line <m>l</m> and a fixed point <m>F</m> are equal.</li>
	<li>Parabolas with vertex at the origin have equations of the form  <me>y=\dfrac{x^2}{4p} ~~~~~~ \text{or} ~~~~~~ y=\dfrac{-x^2}{4p} ~~~~~~ \text{or} ~~~~~~ x=\dfrac{y^2}{4p} ~~~~~~ \text{and} ~~~~~~ x=\dfrac{-y^2}{4p}</me></li>
	<li>The standard equation for an ellipse centered at <m>(h,k)</m> is
			<me>\dfrac{(x-h)^2}{a^2} + \dfrac{(y-k)^2}{b^2} = 1</me></li>
	<li>Second-degree equations  can be written in one of the standard forms by completing the square.</li>
	<li>To write the equation of an ellipse from a description of its properties, we must find the center of the ellipse and the lengths of its axes.</li>
	<li>The standard equations for a hyperbola centered <m>(h,k)</m> at  are
			<me>\dfrac{(x-h)^2}{a^2} - \dfrac{(y-k)^2}{b^2} = 1~~\text{and}~~\dfrac{(y-k)^2}{b^2} - \dfrac{(x-h)^2}{a^2} = 1</me>
		</li>
	<li>The standard equation for a parabola with vertex at  has one of the following forms.
		<me>y-k=a(x-h)^2~~~~~\text{opens upward if}~a \gt 0;~~\text{downward if}~a \lt 0</me>
    	<me>x-h=a(y-k)^2~~~~~\text{opens to the right if}~a \gt 0;~~\text{to the left if}~a \lt 0</me></li>
	<li>The constant <m>a</m> is equal to <m>\dfrac{\pm1}{4p}</m>, where <m>p</m> is the distance between the vertex and the focus of the parabola.</li>  
	<li>The coefficients <m>D, E,</m> and <m>F</m> do not affect the type of conic section the equation represents, but they do determine the position of the graph relative to the origin.</li>
	<li>The graph of a second-degree equation in two variables is a conic section.</li>
	<li><p>The graph of <m>~Ax^2 + Bxy + Cy^2 + Dx + Ey + F = 0~</m> is</p><p><ol label = "1">
    	<li>a circle if <m>A=C</m>.</li>
    	<li>a parabola if <m>A=0</m> or <m>C=0</m> (but not both).</li>
    	<li>an ellipse if <m>A \not= C</m> and they have the same sign.</li>
    	<li>a hyperbola if <m>A</m> and <m>C</m> have opposite signs.</li></ol></p></li>
	<li>Systems involving conics may have up to four solutions.</li>
	<li>To solve some quadratic systems, we can use a combination of elimination of variables and substitution.</li>
	</ol></p>
</subsection>
<!-- <subsubsection> -->
	<xi:include href="./chap10-rev-problems.xml" />   <!-- exercises  -->
<!-- </subsubsection> -->

</section>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->