<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="CentralConics"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<title>Central Conics</title>
    <introduction>
    <p>We know that the graph of any first-degree equation in two variables,
        <me>Ax + By = C</me>
    is a line, as long as <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> are not both <m>0</m>.  We now consider second-degree equations in two variables.  The most general form of such an equation is 
        <me>Ax^2 + Bxy + Cy^2 + Dx + Ey + F = 0</me>
    where <m>A, B</m>, and <m>C</m> cannot all be zero (because in that case the equation would not be second degree).</p>
    <p>The graphs of such equations are curves called <term>conic sections</term> because they are formed by the intersection of a plane and a cone, as shown below.  Except for a few special cases called <term>degenerate conics</term>, which we will describe later, the conic sections fall into four categories called <term>circles, ellipses, hyperbolas,</term> and <term>parabolas.</term></p>

    <sidebyside width="75%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-conics.png"><description>conic sections</description></image></sidebyside>
</introduction>
                
<subsection><title>Circles and Ellipses</title>   
    <p> In this section we will consider conic sections whose centers (or vertices, in the case of parabolas) are located at the origin.  Such curves are called <term>central conics</term>.</p>
    <p>The <term>circle</term> is the most familiar of the conic sections.  We can use the distance formula to derive the standard equation for a circle of radius <m>r</m> centered at the point <m>(h,k)</m>:
        <me>(x-h)^2 + (y-k)^2 = r^2</me>
    A circle whose center is the origin thus has equation 
        <me>x^2+y^2= r^2</me>
    We can also write this equation in the form
        <me>\dfrac{x^2}{r^2} + \dfrac{y^2}{r^2} = 1</me></p>

    <note><p>The denominator of the <m>x</m>-squared term is the square of the <m>x</m>-intercepts,and the denominator of the <m>y</m>-squared term is the square of the <m>y</m>-intercepts. (Do you see why?) Of course, in this case the <m>x</m>- and <m>y</m>-intercepts are equal because the graph is a circle.</p></note>

    <p> If the denominators of the <m>x</m>-squared and <m>y</m>-squared terms are different (but positive), the graph is called an <term>ellipse</term>.  For example, the graph of
        <me>\dfrac{x^2}{9} + \dfrac{y^2}{4} = 1</me>
    is shown below.
        <sidebyside width="45%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-ellipsex.png"><description>conic sections</description></image></sidebyside>  

    When <m>y=0</m>, we have <m>\dfrac{x^2}{9} = 1</m>, so the <m>x</m>-intercepts are <m>(3,0)</m> and <m>(-3,0)</m>. When <m>x=0</m>, we have <m>\dfrac{y^2}{4} = 1</m>,  so the <m>y</m>-intercepts are <m>(0,2)</m> and <m>(0,-2)</m>.</p>
    
    <p>In general, we define an ellipse as follows.</p>

    <assemblage><title>Ellipse</title>
        <p>An <term>ellipse</term> is the set of points in the plane the sum of whose distances from two fixed points (called the <term>foci</term>) is a constant.</p></assemblage>

    <p> We can visualize the definition in the following way.  Drive two nails into a board to represent the two foci.  Attach the two ends of a piece of string to the two nails, and stretch the string taut with a pencil.  Trace around the two nails, keeping the string taut, as illustrated below.  Because the sum of the distances from each point to the two foci is the length of the string, which is constant, the figure described will be an ellipse.</p>

        <sidebyside width="55%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-ellipseboard.png"><description>draw ellipse</description></image></sidebyside>

    <p> Ellipses appear in a variety of applications.  The orbits of the planets about the sun and of satellites about the earth are ellipses.  The arches in some bridges are elliptical in shape, and whispering domes, such as the ceiling of the Mormon Tabernacle in Salt Lake City, are made from ellipses.</p>
    <p>Using the distance formula and the definition above, we can show that the equation of an ellipse centered at the origin has the following form.</p>

    <assemblage><title>Standard Equation for an Ellipse</title>
        <p><me>\dfrac{x^2}{a^2} + \dfrac{y^2}{b^2} = 1</me></p></assemblage>

    <p>From this equation, we discover several features of the graph.</p>
        <p><ul>
        <li>By setting <m>y</m> equal to zero in this equation, we find that the <m>x</m>-intercepts of this ellipse are <m>a</m> and <m>-a</m>; by setting <m>x</m> equal to zero, we find that the <m>y</m>-intercepts are <m>b</m> and <m>-b</m>.</li>  
        <li>The line segment that passes through the foci and ends on the ellipse is called the <term>major axis</term>.  When <m>a \gt b</m>, the foci lie on the <m>x</m>-axis, as shown at left below.</li>
        <li>The <m>x</m>-intercepts are the endpoints of the major axis, so its length is <m>2a</m>.</li>  
        <li>The vertical segment with length <m>2b</m> is called the <term>minor axis</term>.</li>
        <li>The endpoints of the major axis are called the <term>vertices</term> of the ellipse, and the endpoints of the minor axis are the <term>covertices</term>.</li></ul></p>

        <sidebyside width="75%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-ellipsefeatures.png"><description>hor and vert ellipses</description></image></sidebyside>

    <p>When <m>a \lt b</m>, the foci are on the <m>y</m>-axis, as shown at right above. So the <m>y</m>-intercepts of the ellipse are the endpoints of the major axis, which then has length <m>2b</m>. In this case the minor axis is horizontal and has length <m>2a</m>.</p>

    <p>The standard form of the equation for an ellipse gives us enough information to sketch its graph.</p>
    
<example><statement><p>Graph <m>~~\dfrac{x^2}{8} + \dfrac{y^2}{25} = 1</m></p></statement>
    
<solution><p>The graph is an ellipse with major axis on the <m>y</m>-axis.  Because <m>a^2=8</m> and <m>b^2=25</m>, the vertices are located at <m>(0,5)</m> and <m>(0,-5)</m>, and the covertices lie <m>\sqrt{8} = 2\sqrt{2}</m> units to the right and left of the center, or at approximately <m>(2.8,0)</m> and <m>(-2.8,0)</m>.</p>

    <sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">              
                    <row bottom="minor">
                        <cell><m>x</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>y</m></cell></row>
                    <row> 
                        <cell><m>0</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\pm 5</m></cell></row>
                    <row>    
                        <cell><m>\pm 2\sqrt{2}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>0</m></cell></row>
                    </tabular></sidebyside>
    
    <p>To sketch the ellipse, we first locate the vertices and covertices, then draw a smooth curve through the points. </p>

    <sidebyside width="45%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-exm1.png"><description>ellipse</description></image></sidebyside>
</solution></example>

<exercise><statement><p>Graph <m>~~\dfrac{x^2}{16} + \dfrac{y^2}{9} = 1</m></p></statement>

<answer><p><sidebyside width="45%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-exans1.png"><description>ellipse</description></image></sidebyside></p></answer></exercise>

<p>The equation of any central ellipse may be written as
    <me>Ax^2 + By^2 = C</me>
where <m>A, B</m> and <m>C</m> have the same sign. The features of the graph are easier to identify if we first convert the equation to standard form.</p>

<example><statement><p>Graph <m>~~4x^2 + y^2 = 12</m></p></statement>

<solution><p>To convert the equation to standard form, we  divide through by the constant term, 12, and obtain
    <me>\dfrac{x^2}{3} + \dfrac{y^2}{12} = 1</me>
Because <m>a^2=3</m> and <m>b^2=12</m>,  the vertices are <m>(0, \pm\sqrt{12})=(0, \pm2\sqrt{3})</m> and the covertices are 
<m>(\pm\sqrt{3}, 0)</m>.

    <sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">              
                    <row bottom="minor">
                        <cell><m>x</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>y</m></cell></row>
                    <row> 
                        <cell><m>0</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\pm 2\sqrt{3}</m></cell></row>
                    <row>    
                        <cell><m>\pm \sqrt{3}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>0</m></cell></row>
                    </tabular></sidebyside>

We plot points at approximately <m>(0, \pm 3.4)</m> and <m>(\pm 1.7, 0)</m>, then draw a central ellipse through the points.</p>

<sidebyside width="45%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-exm2.png"><description>ellipse</description></image></sidebyside>
</solution></example>

<exercise> <statement><p>Graph <m>~~9x^2 + 8y^2 = 16</m></p></statement>
    
<answer>
    <sidebyside width="35%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-exans2.png"><description>ellipse</description></image></sidebyside>
    </answer></exercise>

<p> We can find coordinates of other points on an ellipse by substituting a value for one variable and solving for the other variable.</p>
    
<example><statement><p><ol label="a">
    <li>Find the exact coordinates of any points with <m>y</m>-coordinate 2 on the ellipse <m>4x^2+y^2=12</m>. Plot and label those points on the ellipse.</li>
<li>Solve the equation <m>4x^2+y^2=12</m> when <m>y=-4</m>. What do the solutions tell you about the graph of the ellipse?</li></ol></p></statement>

<solution><p><ol label="a">
    <li>We substitute <m>y=2</m> in the equation and solve for <m>x</m>.
            <!--*****--><me>\begin{aligned}[t]
                4x^2 + (2)^2 \amp = 12\\
                4x^2 \amp = 8\\
                x^2 \amp = 2\\ 
                x \amp = \pm \sqrt{2}\\                
                \end{aligned}</me><!--*****-->
        There are two points with <m>y=2</m>, namely <m>(\sqrt{2}, 2)</m> and <m>(-\sqrt{2}, 2)</m>, as shown below.

    <sidebyside width="45%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-exm3ans.png"><description>ellipse</description></image></sidebyside>
    </li>
    <li>We substitute <m>y=-4</m> and solve for <m>x</m>.
            <!--*****--><me>\begin{aligned}[t]
                4x^2 + (-4)^2 \amp = 12\\
                4x^2 \amp = -4\\
                x^2 \amp = -1\\ 
                x \amp = \pm i\\                
                \end{aligned}</me><!--*****-->
        There are no real solutions because there are no points on the ellipse with <m>y=-4</m>.</li></ol></p></solution></example>

<exercise> <statement><p>Find the exact coordinates of all points with <m>y</m>-coordinate <m>-1</m> on the ellipse <m>~~9x^2+8y^2=16</m>.</p></statement>
    
<answer><m>(\dfrac{2\sqrt{2}}{3}, -1), ~(\dfrac{-2\sqrt{2}}{3}, -1)</m></answer></exercise>   

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Hyperbolas</title>

 <p>If a cone is cut by a plane parallel to its axis, the intersection is a <term>hyperbola</term>, the only conic section made of two separate pieces, or <term>branches</term>.  Hyperbolas occur in a number of applied settings.  The navigational system called LORAN (long-range navigation) uses radio signals to locate a ship or plane at the intersection of two hyperbolas.  Satellites moving with sufficient speed will follow an orbit that is branch of a hyperbola; for example, a rocket sent to the moon must be fitted with retrorockets to reduce its speed in order to achieve an elliptical, rather than hyperbolic, orbit about the moon.</p>
  <p>The hyperbola is defined as follows.</p>

  <assemblage><title>Hyperbola</title>
    <p>A <term>hyperbola</term> is the set of points in the plane, the difference of whose distances from two fixed points (the <term>foci</term>) is a constant.</p></assemblage>

<p>If the origin is the center of the hyperbola and the foci lie on the <m>x</m>-axis, we can show that its equation may be written as follows.</p>

    <assemblage><title>Standard Equation for a Hyperbola</title>
    <p><me>\dfrac{x^2}{a^2} - \dfrac{y^2}{b^2} = 1</me></p></assemblage>

<p> A hyperbola with this equation has the following features:</p><p><ul>
    <li> The two branches of the hyperbola open left and right, so the graph has <m>x</m>-intercepts at <m>a</m> and <m>-a</m>, but no <m>y</m>-intercepts, as shown below.</li>  
    <li>The segment joining the <m>x</m>-intercepts is the <term>transverse axis</term>, and its length is <m>2a</m>.</li>
    <li>The segment of length <m>2b</m> is called the <term>conjugate axis</term>.</li>
    <li>The endpoints of the transverse axis are the <term>vertices</term> of the hyperbola.</li></ul></p>

<sidebyside width="45%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-hyperbx.png"><description>hyperbola</description></image></sidebyside>

<p>A hyperbola centered at the origin with foci on the <m>y</m>-axis has the following equation.</p>

<assemblage><title>Standard Equarion for a Hyperbola</title>
    <p><me>\dfrac{y^2}{b^2} - \dfrac{x^2}{a^2} = 1</me></p></assemblage>

 <p>In this case the graph has <m>y</m>-intercepts at <m>b</m> and <m>-b</m>, but no <m>x</m>-intercepts, because the two branches open up and down. Here the <m>y</m>-intercepts are the vertices, so the transverse axis is vertical and has length <m>2b</m>.  The conjugate axis has length <m>2a</m>. A typical example is shown below.</p>     
    
<sidebyside width="45%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-hyperby.png"><description>hyperbola</description></image></sidebyside>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Asymptotes of Hyperbolas</title>

<p>The branches of the hyperbola approach two straight lines that intersect at its center.  These lines are <term>asymptotes</term> of the graph, and they are useful as guidelines for sketching the hyperbola.  We can draw the asymptotes by first forming the "central rectangle," whose sides pass through the vertices and covertices.  The asymptotes are the diagonals of this rectangle.</p>

<example><statement><p>Graph <m>~~\dfrac{y^2}{9} - \dfrac{x^2}{4} = 1</m></p></statement>
    
<solution><p>The graph is a hyperbola with center at the origin. The branches of the hyperbola open upward and downward, so the vertices lie on the <m>y</m>-axis. Also, <m>a^2=4</m> and <m>b^2=9</m>, so <m>a=2</m> and <m>b=3</m>. The vertices of the hyperbola are <m>(0,3)</m> and <m>(0,-3)</m>. There are no <m>x</m>-intercepts.</p>
<p>We construct the central rectangle with dimensions <m>2a=4</m> and <m>2b=6</m>, as shown below. Then we draw the asymptotes through the diagonals of the rectangle. (Note that the asymptotes have slopes <m>\pm \dfrac{3}{2}</m>.) Finally, we sketch the branches of the hyperbola through the vertices and approaching the asymptotes to obtain the graph shown.</p>

<sidebyside width="45%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-exm4ans.png"><description>hyperbola</description></image></sidebyside>
    
</solution></example>

<exercise> <statement><p>Follow the steps to graph <m>~~\dfrac{x^2}{9} - \dfrac{y^2}{16} = 1</m></p>
    <p>Find <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>, and plot the vertices.</p>
    <p>Sketch the central rectangle.</p>
    <p>Draw the asymptotes.</p>
    <p>Sketch the hyperbola.</p>
</statement>
    
<answer>
    <sidebyside width="35%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-exans4.png"><description>hyperbola</description></image></sidebyside>
    </answer></exercise>

 <note><p>In the examples above, note that the slopes of the asymptotes are <m>\pm \dfrac{b}{a}</m>.</p></note>

 <p>The equation of a central hyperbola may be written as
        <me>Ax^2 + By^2 = C</me>
    where <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> have <em>opposite</em> signs and <m>C \not= 0</m>.  For example,
    <me>2x^2-3y^2=6 ~~~~~~\text{and} ~~~~~~ -4x^2+y^2=3</me>
    are equations of hyperbolas.  As with ellipses, it is best to rewrite the equation in standard form in order to graph it.</p>

 <example><statement><p>Write the equation <m>~~4y^2-x^2=16~~</m> in standard form and describe the important features of its graph.</p></statement>

<solution><p>We first divide each side by 16 to obtain
    <me> \dfrac{y^2}{4} - \dfrac{x^2}{16} = 1 ~~~~~~\text{or} ~~~~~~ \dfrac{y^2}{2^2} - \dfrac{x^2}{4^2} = 1</me>
The graph is a central hyperbola with <m>y</m>-intercepts <m>2</m> and <m>-2</m>.  The slopes of the asymptotes are given by
    <me>\pm \dfrac{b}{a}=\pm \dfrac{2}{4}=\pm \dfrac{1}{2} </me>
so the equations of the asymptotes are <m>y= \dfrac{1}{2} x</m> and <m>y= \dfrac{-1}{2} x</m>.</p>

  <sidebyside width="45%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-exm5ans.png"><description>hyperbola</description></image></sidebyside>  
    
</solution></example>

<exercise><statement><p><ol label = "a">
    <li>Write the equation <m>4x^2 = y^2 + 25</m> in standard form.</li>
    <li>Find the vertices of the graph and the equations of the asymptotes.</li></ol></p></statement>
    
<answer><p><ol label = "a">
    <li><m>\dfrac{x^2}{(\dfrac{5}{2})^2} - \dfrac{y^2}{5^2}=1</m></li>
    <li><m>(\dfrac{5}{2}, 0), ~(\dfrac{-5}{2}, 0), ~~y=2x, ~y=-2x</m></li></ol></p></answer></exercise>

<p>We can find exact coordinates of points on a hyperbola by substituting a value for one variable and solving for the other variable.</p>
    
<example><statement><p>Find the exact coordinates of any points with <m>x</m>-coordinate <m>x=2</m> on the hyperbola with equation <m>4x^2-y^2=16</m>. Plot and label those points on the hyperbola.</p></statement>

<solution><p>We substitute  in the given equation.
    <!--*****--><me>\begin{aligned}[t]
                4y^2 - (2)^2 \amp = 16\\
                4y^2 \amp = 20\\
                y^2 \amp = 5\\ 
                y \amp = \pm \sqrt{5}\\                
                \end{aligned}</me><!--*****-->

    There are two points with <m>x=2</m>, namely <m>(2, \sqrt{5})</m> and <m>(2, -\sqrt{5})</m>, as shown in the figure.</p>

  <sidebyside width="45%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-exm6ans.png"><description>hyperbola</description></image></sidebyside>  
    
</solution></example>

<exercise><statement><p>Solve the equation <m>4y^2-x^2=16</m> when <m>y=1</m>.  What is the significance of the solutions to the graph of the hyperbola?</p></statement>
    
<answer><p>There are no solutions when <m>y=1</m> because there are no points on the hyperbola with <m>y=1</m>.</p>
</answer></exercise>
</subsection>

<subsection><title>Parabolas</title>

<p>If a cone is cut by a plane parallel to the side of the cone, the intersection is a parabola.  We have already graphed parabolas whose equations were of the form
    <me>y=ax^2+bx+c</me>
These parabolas opened either up or down and had vertical axes of symmetry. However, it is also possible to have parabolas that open to the left or right. In general, we define a parabola as follows.</p>

<assemblage><title>Parabola</title>
<p>A <term>parabola</term> is the set of points in the plane whose distances from a fixed line <m>l</m> and a fixed point <m>F</m> are equal.</p></assemblage>

<p> The fixed line in the definition is called the <term>directrix</term>, and the fixed point is the <term>focus</term>. The <term>axis</term> of a parabola is the line running through the focus of the parabola and perpendicular to the directrix.</p> 

<sidebyside width="80%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-parabs.png"><description>parabolas</description></image></sidebyside>

<p> Parabolas have many applications in optics and communications.  Parabolic mirrors are used in telescopes because light waves received reflect off the surface and form an image at the focus of the parabola.  For similar reasons radio antennae and television dish receivers are parabolic in shape.  The parabolic mirrors in searchlights and automobile headlights reflect light from the focus into beams of parallel rays.</p>
<p>We first consider parabolas with vertex at the origin, as shown below.</p>

<sidebyside width="80%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-centparabs.png"><description>central parabolas</description></image></sidebyside>

<p>Using the distance formula and the definition above, it can be shown that parabolas that open upward and those that open downward have equations of the forms
    <me>y=\dfrac{x^2}{4p} ~~~~~~ \text{and} ~~~~~~ y=\dfrac{-x^2}{4p}</me>
respectively, where <m>p</m> is the distance between the vertex of the parabola and its focus,or the distance between the vertex and the directrix.</p>  
<p> Parabolas that open to the right and those that open to the left have equations of the forms
    <me>x=\dfrac{y^2}{4p} ~~~~~~ \text{and} ~~~~~~ x=\dfrac{-y^2}{4p}</me>
respectively.</p>

<p> A line drawn through the focus and parallel to the directrix will intersect the parabola at two points.  These points are <m>2p</m> units from the directrix, so they must also be <m>2p</m> units from the focus.  (Recall that by definition the points of a parabola are equidistant from the focus and the directrix.)</p>  

<sidebyside width="45%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-guidepts.png"><description>parabolas</description></image></sidebyside>

<p>By locating these two "guide points" and the vertex, we can make a reasonable sketch of the parabola, as illustrated in the next example.</p>

<example><statement><p>Graph <m>~~x = \dfrac{-y^2}{6}~~</m> </p></statement>

<solution><p>The parabola has its vertex at the origin and opens to the left, so its axis is the <m>x</m>-axis. Also, <m>6=4p</m>, so <m>p=\dfrac{3}{2}</m>, and the focus is the point <m>(-\dfrac{3}{2}, 0)</m>. The directrix is the vertical line <m>x=\dfrac{3}{2}</m></p>.
<p>To graph the parabola, we draw a line segment of length <m>4p=6</m> perpendicular to the axis and centered at the focus.  Because <m>2p=3</m>, the endpoints of the segment are <m>(-\dfrac{3}{2}, 3)</m> and <m>(-\dfrac{3}{2}, -3)</m>.  We sketch the parabola through the vertex and the two guide points to obtain the graph shown below.</p>

  <sidebyside width="45%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-exm7ans.png"><description>parabola</description></image></sidebyside>  
    
</solution></example>

<exercise><statement><p>Graph <m>~~y^2-8x=0</m></p></statement>
    
<answer><p><sidebyside width="35%"><image source="images/fig-10-1-exans7.png"><description>parabola</description></image></sidebyside>  </p></answer></exercise>

<example><statement><p>Write each equation in standard form and describe its graph.</p>
<p><ol label="a" cols="2">
    <li><m>x^2=9y^2-9</m></li>
    <li><m>4x^2+y=0</m></li>
    <li><m>9y^2=4-x^2</m></li>
    <li><m>6x^2=18-6y^2</m></li></ol></p></statement>

 <solution><p><ol label="a">
 <li>The equation <m>x^2=9y^2-9</m> is equivalent to
        <me>9y^2-x^2=9 ~~~~~~ \text{or} ~~~~~~ \dfrac{y^2}{1^2} - \dfrac{x^2}{3^2}=1</me>   
    The graph is a hyperbola opening up and down.</li>
 <li>The equation <m>4x^2+y=0</m> is equivalent to
        <me>y=-4x^2 ~~~~~~ \text{or} ~~~~~~ y= \dfrac{-x^2}{\dfrac{1}{4}}</me>   
    The graph is a parabola that opens downward.</li>   
 <li>The equation <m>9y^2=4-x^2</m> is equivalent to
        <me>x^2+9y^2=4 ~~~~~~ \text{or} ~~~~~~ \dfrac{x^2}{(2)^2} + \dfrac{y^2}{(\dfrac{2}{3})^2}=1</me>   
    The graph is an ellipse with major axis on the <m>x</m>-axis because <m>2 \gt \dfrac{2}{3}</m>.</li>
 <li>The equation <m>6x^2=18-6y^2</m> is equivalent to
        <me>6x^2+6y^2=18 ~~~~~~ \text{or} ~~~~~~ x^2 + y^2 = (\sqrt{3})^2</me>   
    The graph is a circle with radius <m>\sqrt{3}</m>.</li>
 </ol></p></solution></example>

 <exercise><statement><p>Write each equation in standard form and describe its graph.</p>
<p><ol label="a" cols="2">
    <li><m>x^2=6y^2+8</m></li>
    <li><m>x^2=\dfrac{4-y^2}{2}</m></li></ol></p></statement>

<answer><p><ol label="a"> 
    <li><p><m>\dfrac{x^2}{(\sqrt{8})^2} - \dfrac{y^2}{(\dfrac{2}{\sqrt{3}})^2}=1</m></p>   
    <p>The graph is a hyperbola that opens left and right.</p></li>   
    <li><p><m>\dfrac{x^2}{(\sqrt{2})^2} + \dfrac{y^2}{2^2}=1</m></p>   
    <p>The graph is an ellipse with major axis on the <m>y</m>-axis because <m>2 \gt \sqrt{2}</m>.</p></li></ol></p></answer></exercise>

</subsection>

<!-- <xi:include href="./summary-10-1.xml" /> summary  
<xi:include href="./section-10-1-exercises.xml" /> exercises  -->

</section> 
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->