<?xml version="1.0"?>


<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!--   Applied Algebra   -->
<!--           4th                                     -->
<!-- Copyright (C) Sean Laverty (with others, via Katherine Yoshiwara)      -->

<exercises xml:id="section-9-3-exercises"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Homework 9.3</title>

<exercisegroup>
    <introduction><p>For Problems 1<ndash/>6, evaluate the arithmetic series.</p></introduction>

    <exercise number="1"><statement><p>The sum of the first nine terms of the sequence <m>~a_n = -4 + 3n</m></p></statement>
        <answer><m>99</m>  </answer></exercise>

    <exercise number="2"><statement><p>The sum of the first ten terms of the sequence <m>~a_n = 5-2n</m></p></statement></exercise>

    <exercise number="3"><statement><p>The sum of the first 16 terms of the sequence <m>~a_n = 18-\dfrac{4}{3}n</m></p></statement>
        <answer><m>106\dfrac{2}{3}</m>  </answer></exercise>

    <exercise number="4"><statement><p>The sum of the first 13 terms of the sequence <m>~a_n = -6 - \dfrac{1}{2}n</m></p></statement></exercise>

    <exercise number="5"><statement><p>The sum of the first 30 terms of the sequence <m>~a_n = 1.6+0.2n</m></p></statement>
        <answer><m>141</m>  </answer></exercise>

    <exercise number="6"><statement><p>The sum of the first 25 terms of the sequence <m>~a_n = 2.5+0.3n</m></p></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercisegroup>
    <introduction><p>For Problems 7<ndash/>12, evaluate the geometricc series.</p></introduction>

    <exercise number="7"><statement><p>The sum of the first five terms of <m>a_n = 2(-4)^{n-1}</m></p></statement>
        <answer><m>410</m>  </answer></exercise>

    <exercise number="8"><statement><p>The sum of the first eight terms of <m>a_n = 12(3)^{n-1}</m></p></statement></exercise>

    <exercise number="9"><statement><p>The sum of the first nine terms of <m>a_n = -48(\dfrac{1}{2})^{n-1}</m></p></statement>
        <answer><m>-95.8125</m>  </answer></exercise>

    <exercise number="10"><statement><p>The sum of the first six terms of <m>a_n = 81(\dfrac{2}{3})^{n-1}</m></p></statement></exercise> 

    <exercise number="11"><statement><p>The sum of the first four terms of <m>a_n = 18(1.15)^{n-1}</m></p></statement>
        <answer><m>89.88075</m>  </answer></exercise>

    <exercise number="12"><statement><p>The sum of the first four terms of <m>a_n = 512(0.72)^{n-1}</m></p></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercisegroup ><introduction><p>For Problems 13<ndash/>22, identify the series as arithmetic, geometric or neither, then evaluate it.</p></introduction>

    <exercise number="13"><statement><m>2+4+6+\cdots+96+98+100</m></statement>
        <answer><p>Arithemtic; 2550</p>  </answer></exercise>

    <exercise number="14"><statement><m>1+3+5+\cdots+95+97+99</m></statement></exercise>

    <exercise number="15"><statement><m>2+4+8+16+\cdots+256+512+1024</m></statement>
    <answer><p>Geometric; 2046</p>  </answer></exercise>

    <exercise number="16"><statement><m>1+3+9+27+\cdots+6561+19,683</m></statement></exercise>

    <exercise number="17"><statement><m>1+8+24+64+125+216+343</m></statement>
    <answer><p>Neither; 784</p>  </answer></exercise>

    <exercise number="18"><statement><m>1+11+111+1111+11,111+111,111</m></statement></exercise>

    <exercise number="19"><statement><m>87+84+81+78+\cdots+45+42+39</m></statement>
    <answer><p>Arithmetic; 1071</p>  </answer></exercise>

    <exercise number="20"><statement><m>1+(-2)+(-5)+\cdots+(-41)+(-44)</m></statement></exercise>

    <exercise number="21"><statement><m>6+2+\dfrac{2}{3}+\cdots+\dfrac{2}{81}+\dfrac{2}{243}</m></statement>
    <answer><p>Geometric; 8.996</p>  </answer></exercise>

    <exercise number="22"><statement><m>12+3+\dfrac{3}{4}+\cdots+\dfrac{3}{64}+\dfrac{3}{128}</m></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>  

<exercisegroup><introduction><p>For Problems 23<ndash/>40, write a series to describe the problem, then evaluate it.</p></introduction>

<exercise number="23"><statement><p>Find the sum of all the even integers from 14 to 88.</p></statement>
    <answer><m>1938</m>  </answer></exercise>

<exercise number="24"><statement><p>Find the sum of all multiples of 7 from 14 to 105.</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="25"><statement><p>A clock strikes once at one o'clock, twice at two o'clock, and so on.  How many times will the clock strike in a twelve hour period?</p></statement>
    <answer><m>78</m>  </answer></exercise>

<exercise number="26"><statement><p>Jessica puts one candle on the cake at her daughter's first birthday, two candles at her second birthday, and so on. How many candles will Jessica have used after her daughter's sixteenth birthday?</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="27"><statement><p>A rubber ball is dropped from a height of 24 feet and returns to three-fourths of its previous height on each bounce.</p><p><ol label="a">  
    <li>How high does the ball bounce after hitting the floor for the third time?</li>
    <li>How far has the ball traveled vertically when it hits the floor for the fourth time?</li></ol></p></statement>
    <answer><p><ol label="a">
        <li>10.125 ft</li>
        <li>107.25 ft</li></ol></p>  </answer></exercise>

<exercise number="28"><statement><p>A Yorkshire terrier can jump 3 feet into the air on his first bounce and five-sixths the height of his previous jump on each successive bounce.</p><p><ol label="a">
   <li>How high can the terrier go on his fourth bounce?</li>
    <li>How far has the terrier traveled vertically when he returns to the ground after his fourth bounce?</li></ol></p>
</statement></exercise>

<exercise number="29"><statement><p>Sales of Brussels Sprouts dolls peaked at $920,000 in 1991 and began to decline at a steady rate of $40,000 per year. What total revenue did the manufacturer gain from sale of the dolls from 1991 to 2000?</p></statement>
    <answer><p>$7,400,000</p>  </answer></exercise>

<exercise number="30"><statement><p>It takes Alida 20 minutes to type the first page of her term paper, but each subsequent page takes her 40 seconds less than the previous one.  How long will it take her to type her 30-page paper?</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="31"><statement><p>A computer takes 0.1 second to perform the first iteration of a certain loop, and each subsequent iteration takes 0.05 seconds longer than the previous one.  How long will it take the computer to perform 50 iterations?</p></statement>
    <answer><p>66.25 sec</p> </answer></exercise>

<exercise number="32"><statement><p>Richard's water bill was $63.50 last month.  If his bill increases by $2.30 per month, how much should he expect to pay for water during the next 10 months?</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="33"><statement><p>Sales of Energy Ranger dolls peaked at $920,000 in 2001 and began to decline by 8%  per year.  What total revenue did the manufacturer gain from sale of the dolls from 2001 to 2010?</p></statement>
    <answer><p>$6,504,532.78</p>  </answer></exercise>

<exercise number="34"><statement><p>It takes Emily 20 minutes to type the first page of her term paper, but each subsequent page takes only 95% as long as the previous one. How long will it take her to type her 30-page paper?</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="35"><statement><p>A computer takes 0.1 second to perform the first iteration of a certain loop, and each subsequent iteration requires 20% longer than the previous one. How long will it take the computer to perform 50 iterations?</p></statement>
    <answer><p>4540.7 sec</p>  </answer></exercise>

<exercise number="36"><statement><p>Megan's water bill was $63.50 last month. If her bill increases by 2% per month, how much should she expect to pay for water during the next 10 months?</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="37"><statement><p>Jim and Nora begin a college fund for their son David by depositing $500 into an account each year, beginning on the day David was born.  If the account earns an interest rate of 5% compounded annually, how much will be in the account on David's eighteenth birthday?</p></statement>
    <answer><p>$15,269.50</p>  </answer></exercise>

<exercise number="38"><statement><p>Ben begins an Individual Retirement Account when he turns 25 years old, depositing $2000 into the account each year.  If the account earns 6% interest compounded annually, how much will he have in the account when he turns 65 years old?</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="39"><statement><p>Suppose that you are given 1¢ on the first day of the month, 2¢ on the second day, 4¢ on the third day, and so on, each day's payment being twice the previous day's.  What would be your total income on the thirtieth day?
</p></statement>
    <answer><p>$10,737,418.23</p>  </answer></exercise>

<exercise number="40"><statement><p>According to legend, a man who had pleased the Persian king asked for the following reward.  The man was to receive a single grain of wheat for the first square of a chessboard, two grains for the second square,  four grains for the third square, and so on, doubling the amount for each square up to the sixty-fourth square.  How many grains would he receive in all?
</p></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

</exercises>
