<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<subsection xml:id="summary-10-1" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Section Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title>
<p>
	Look up the definitions of new terms in the Glossary.
	<ul cols="3">
		<li>Ellipse</li>
		<li>Hyperbola</li>
		<li>Central conic</li>
		<li>Focus</li>
		<li> Major axis</li>
		<li>Minor axis</li>
		<li>Vertex</li>	
		<li>Covertex</li>	
		<li>Transverse axis</li>
		<li>Conjugate axis</li>	
		<li>Asymptote</li>	
		<li>Directrix</li></ul></p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>CONCEPTS</title>
<p><ol label="1">
	<li>The most general form of a second-degree equation in two variables is 
        <me>Ax^2 + Bxy + Cy^2 + Dx + Ey + F = 0</me>
    where <m>A, B</m>, and <m>C</m> cannot all be zero, and its graph is a conic section.</li>
	<li>An ellipse is the set of points in the plane the sum of whose distances from two fixed points (called the foci) is a constant.</li>
	<li>The standard form for an ellipse centered at the origin is
			<me>\dfrac{x^2}{a^2} + \dfrac{y^2}{b^2} = 1</me></li>
	<li>A hyperbola is the set of points in the plane, the difference of whose distances from two fixed points (the foci) is a constant.</li>
	<li>The standard form for a hyperbola centered at the origin with foci on the <m>x</m>-axis is
			<me>\dfrac{x^2}{a^2} - \dfrac{y^2}{b^2} = 1</me>
	The standard form for a hyperbola centered at the origin with foci on the <m>y</m>-axis is
		<me>\dfrac{y^2}{b^2} - \dfrac{x^2}{a^2} = 1</me></li>
	<li>We can draw the asymptotes by first forming the "central rectangle," whose sides pass through the vertices and covertices.  The asymptotes are the diagonals of this rectangle.</li>
	<li>A parabola is the set of points in the plane whose distances from a fixed line <m>l</m> and a fixed point <m>F</m> are equal.</li>
	<li>Parabolas with vertex at the origin have equations of the form  <me>y=\dfrac{x^2}{4p} ~~~~~~ \text{or} ~~~~~~ y=\dfrac{-x^2}{4p} ~~~~~~ \text{or} ~~~~~~ x=\dfrac{y^2}{4p} ~~~~~~ \text{and} ~~~~~~ x=\dfrac{-y^2}{4p}</me></li>
	</ol></p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li>Name four types of conic sections.  Why are they called conic sections?</li>
		<li>Define the following terms related to ellipses:  major and minor axes, vertices and covertices.</li>
		<li>What is the standard form for the equation of an ellipse?</li>
		<li>Define the following terms related to hyperbolas:  transverse and conjugate axes, vertices, asymptotes.</li>
		<li>What is the standard form for the equation of a hyperbola?</li>
		<li>What are the directrix and focus of a parabola?</li></ol></p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>SKILLS</title><p>
	Practice each skill in the <xref ref="section-10-1-exercises" text="global">Homework</xref> problems listed.
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Graph circles, ellipses, hyperbolas, and parabolas: #1<ndash />28</p></li>
		<li><p>Find points on the graph with a given coordinate: #29<ndash />40</p></li>
		<li><p>Find an equation for a conic section: #41<ndash />44</p></li>
		<li><p>Find and use an equation for a conic section in an applied situation: #45<ndash />56</p></li></ol>
</p></subsubsection> 

</subsection>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->