<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<subsection xml:id="summary-9-2" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Section Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title>
<p><ul cols="2">
		<li>Arithmetic sequence</li>
		<li>Common difference</li>
		<li>General term</li>
		<li>Geometric sequence</li>
		<li>Common ratio</li>
		<li>Recursive sequence</li>
	</ul></p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>CONCEPTS</title>
<p><ol label="1">
	<li>A sequence in which each term can be obtained from the previous term by adding a fixed amount is called an <term>arithmetic sequence</term>.</li>
	<li>The fixed amount between two successive terms of an arithmetic sequence is called the <term>common difference</term>.</li>
	<li>An arithmetic sequence defines a linear function of <m>n</m>.</li>
	<li>The <m>n^{\text{th}}</m> term of an arithmetic sequence is <m>a_n = a + (n-1)d</m>.</li>
	<li>A sequence in which each term can be obtained from the previous term by multiplying by a fixed amount is called a <term>geometric sequence</term>.</li>
	<li>The ratio of two successive terms of a geometridc sequence is called the <term>common ratio</term>.</li>
	<li>A geometric sequence defines an exponential function of <m>n</m>.</li>
	<li>The <m>n^{\text{th}}</m> term of a geometric sequence is <m>a_n = ar^{n-1}</m>.</li></ol></p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li>What is an arithmetic sequence?  What is the common difference?</li>
		<li>State a formula for the general term of an arithemetic sequence.</li>
		<li>An arithmetic sequence defines what kind of function of <m>n</m>?</li>
		<li>What is a geometric sequence?  What is the common ratio?</li>
		<li>State a formula for the general term of a geometric sequence.</li>
		<li>A geometric sequence defines what kind of function of <m>n</m>?</li></ol></p>
	</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>SKILLS</title><p>
	Practice each skill in the Homework Problems listed.
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Identify arithmetic and geometric sequences: #1<ndash />10</p></li>
		<li><p>Evaluate the general term of an arithmetic or geometric sequence:    #13<ndash />24, #33<ndash />36,</p></li>
		<li><p>Write an expression for the general term:  #25<ndash />38</p></li>
		<li><p>Find the general term from a recursive definition: #41<ndash />48</p></li>
		<li><p>Use a sequence as a model: #49<ndash />56</p></li></ol></p>
	</subsubsection> 

</subsection>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->