<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<subsection xml:id="summary-10-2" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Section Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title>
<p>
	Look up the definitions of new terms in the Glossary.
	<ul cols="3">
		<li>Translation</li>
		<li>Degenerate conic</li></ul></p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>CONCEPTS</title>
<p><ol label="1">
	<li>The standard equation for an ellipse centered at <m>(h,k)</m> is
			<me>\dfrac{(x-h)^2}{a^2} + \dfrac{(y-k)^2}{b^2} = 1</me></li>
	<li>Second-degree equations  can be written in one of the standard forms by completing the square.</li>
	<li>To write the equation of an ellipse from a description of its properties, we must find the center of the ellipse and the lengths of its axes.</li>
	<li>The standard equations for a hyperbola centered <m>(h,k)</m> at  are
			<me>\dfrac{(x-h)^2}{a^2} - \dfrac{(y-k)^2}{b^2} = 1~~\text{and}~~\dfrac{(y-k)^2}{b^2} - \dfrac{(x-h)^2}{a^2} = 1</me>
		</li>
	<li>The standard equation for a parabola with vertex at  has one of the following forms.
		<me>y-k=a(x-h)^2~~~~~\text{opens upward if}~a \gt 0;~~\text{downward if}~a \lt 0</me>
    	<me>x-h=a(y-k)^2~~~~~\text{opens to the right if}~a \gt 0;~~\text{to the left if}~a \lt 0</me></li>
	<li>The constant <m>a</m> is equal to <m>\dfrac{\pm1}{4p}</m>, where <m>p</m> is the distance between the vertex and the focus of the parabola.</li>  
	<li>The coefficients <m>D, E,</m> and <m>F</m> do not affect the type of conic section the equation represents, but they do determine the position of the graph relative to the origin.</li>
	<li>The graph of a second-degree equation in two variables is a conic section.</li>
	<li><p>The graph of <m>~Ax^2 + Bxy + Cy^2 + Dx + Ey + F = 0~</m> is</p><p><ol label = "1">
    	<li>a circle if <m>A=C</m>.</li>
    	<li>a parabola if <m>A=0</m> or <m>C=0</m> (but not both).</li>
    	<li>an ellipse if <m>A \not= C</m> and they have the same sign.</li>
    	<li>a hyperbola if <m>A</m> and <m>C</m> have opposite signs.</li></ol></p></li>
	</ol></p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li>What is a translated conic?</li>
		<li>How is the equation for a translated conic different from the equation for the corresponding central conic?</li>
		<li>What algebraic technique is used to write the equation of a translated conic in standard form?</li>
		<li>Quadratic equations in which the <m>x^2</m> and <m>y^2</m> terms have opposite signs describe which type of conic?</li>
		<li>How can we recognize that a general quadratic equation describes a parabola?</li></ol></p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>SKILLS</title><p>
	Practice each skill in the <xref ref="section-10-2-exercises" text="global">Homework</xref> problems listed.
	<ol label="1">
		<li>Graph a conic section given in standard form:    #1-6, 21-26, 37-40</li>
		<li>Write the equation for a conic section in standard form, and graph it:    #7-14, 27-32, 41-46</li>
		<li>Write an equation ofr a conic section with given properties:    #15-20, 33-36</li>
		<li>Identify and describe a conic section from its equation:    #47-58</li></ol></p>
</subsubsection> 

</subsection>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->