<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chap-the-joy-of-x">
<title> The Joy of <m>X</m> </title>

<introduction>
<p>Two key themes are abstraction and generalization. This includes the
flexibility to abstract from arithmetic calculations with specific
quantities to algebraic work with symbols representing those quantities.
This allows us to move from a very specific situation towards studying
other problems that fit a similar pattern.</p>
</introduction>


<section xml:id="sec-From-arithmetic-to-algebra">
<title> From arithmetic to algebra </title>

<introduction> <p>
Previously we discussed a situation where we know we have run for 25
minutes and covered 5 km or <me>\dfrac{25 \text{minutes}}{5
\text{km}}</me>
Now, say we ran other races or friends have other times at the same
race. Rather than repeat the calculation at each instance, we could
think of generalizing this thought process and building a formula that
works for any time represented by the value of the symbol <m>x</m>. We
would begin by
<me>\dfrac{x \text{minutes}}{5 \cancel{\text{km}}}\times\dfrac{1.609 \
cancel{\text{km}}}{1 \text{mi}} =
0.3218x \dfrac{\text{minutes}}{\text{mi}}</me></p>

<p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>With this we would say that given a time <m>x</m> our pace is given
by
<me>\text{pace}= 0.3218x \dfrac{\text{minutes}}{\text{mi}}</me> Then we
could
consider calculations of <me>any</me> reasonable value for <m>x</m>, or
time in minutes. For example,</p>

<table xml:id="tab-pace">
<title>Pace for a few lengths of time.</title>
<tabular halign="center" left="minor" right="minor" top="minor"
bottom="minor">
<row><cell><m>x</m> </cell> <cell> <m>\text{pace} =
0.3218x</m></cell></row>
<row><cell>15 </cell> <cell> 4.827</cell></row>
<row><cell>20 </cell> <cell> 6.436</cell></row>
<row><cell>25 </cell> <cell> 8.045</cell></row>
<row><cell>30 </cell> <cell> 9.654</cell></row>
</tabular>
</table>

<p>You might notice that multiplication by <m>0.3218</m> is a rather
specific
detail and ask if, as you were running with your eye on the watch, you
could do a reasonable job estimating your pace with a simpler
calculation. We could argue that <me>0.3218 \approx 0.333\dots =
\sfrac{1}{3}</me> noticing this we might consider
<me>0.3218x\approx\left(\sfrac{1}{3}\right)x</me> and furthermore that
multiplication by <m>\sfrac{1}{3}</m> is equivalent to division by
<m>3</m>. We could reasonably approximate our pace by <me>\text{pace} =
\sfrac{x}{3}</me> which might be a bit easier than multiplying by
<m>0.3218</m> in your tired mind.</p>


<table xml:id="tab-pace2">
<title>Pace for a few lengths of time, but also
quickly approximated by a simpler calculation.</title>
<tabular halign="center" left="minor" right="minor" top="minor"
bottom="minor">
<row><cell><m>x</m> </cell> <cell> <m>\text{pace} =
0.3218x</m></cell><cell> <m>\text{pace} \approx
\sfrac{x}{3}</m></cell></row>
<row><cell>15 </cell> <cell> 4.827</cell><cell> 5.000</cell></row>
<row><cell>20 </cell> <cell> 6.436</cell><cell> 6.666</cell></row>
<row><cell>25 </cell> <cell> 8.045</cell><cell> 8.333</cell></row>
<row><cell>30 </cell> <cell> 9.654</cell><cell> 10.00</cell></row>
</tabular>
</table>


<p>It is worth pointing out that we spend most of our time in math
classes
(and other classes) looking at problems that we can solve exactly and to
a unique answer. This is not the case in almost any real situation.
Approximation is valid and valuable as a strategy, we do just need to be
aware of the error we introduce and its consequences. Entire fields of
advanced mathematics are devoted to such issues. The limitations of
doing arithmetic on base-2 computers? That is a big part of numerical
analysis. How important is a specific (and often `small') term in a
great big formula? That is a big part of perturbation theory.</p>

<p><!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... --></p>

</section>

<section xml:id="sec-From-formulas-to-functions">
<title> From formulas to functions </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>
Given a formula we are really just a step away from thinking of
functions. While a function has some extra mathematical properties, we
can really think of a function <m>f(x)</m> as the label for a particular
calculation involving the quantity <m>x</m>. The major string attached
to
this designation is that a particular <m>x</m>-value can only give rise
to
a single calculated value.</p>

<p>Imagine referring to the calculation of the quantity
<m>(50+x)(50+x)</m>,
it would be a bit of a drag if, any time that we wanted to make
reference to the calculation, we had to refer to the complete formula.
Instead we could assign this special calculation to a function <m>f(x) =
(50+x)(50+x)</m>, at which point we could refer to our action by either
the formula or the function name. Setting <m>x = 3</m> and calculating
we
could say ''lets take the quantity <m>50</m> plus <m>3</m> times the
quantity
<m>50</m> plus <m>3</m>'' to calculate a particular value. As a much
more
convenient alternative we could simply say <m>f(3)</m>, the value of the
function whose formula defines the calculation.</p>

<p>Now, a major source of confusion about functions lies in the notation
itself. In particular, parentheses show up in two places, with two
different meanings, 
<me>\underbrace{f(x)}_{\text{function notation}}= \underbrace{(50 +
x)(50
+ x)}_{\text{grouping and multiplication}}</me>
We read the notation <m>f(x)</m> as ''<m>f</m> of <m>x</m>'' referring
to the
value generated by a particular choice of <m>x</m>; these parentheses
serve
as `function notation'. In contrast, each pair of parentheses on the
right (''<m>(50 + x)</m>'') serve as grouping the two terms to be added;
abutting these two factors indicates a step of multiplying the results
of the two completed addition operations. </p>

<p>As an added example of the use and misuse of parenthesis with respect
to
function notation consider the natural logarithm function <m>\ln(x)</m>.
When solving equations that require the application of natural
logarithms for simplification, novice users often write things like
<m>3\cdot \ln</m> when they mean, or should mean, <m>\ln(3)</m>. This
can be
contrasted with how we use the square root symbol
`<m>\sqrt{\phantom{8}}</m>'. To take the square root of <m>8</m>, we
would
always write `<m>\sqrt{8}</m>' and not
`<m>8\cdot\sqrt{\phantom{8}}</m>.'</p>

<p>Sometimes we say <m>y = f(x)</m> to indicate that a particular
function
<m>f(x)</m> generates a value called <m>y</m>, to form an ordered pair
<m>(x,
y)</m>. Occasionally we try to use more meaningful symbols than
<m>y</m>,
<m>f</m>, and <m>x</m>. For example, in discussing our pace we could
somewhat
generically write a function <m>f(x) = 0.3218x</m>. This gives very
little
insight into the meaning of the symbol <m>x</m> or the result of the
calculation. We might then say <m>p = f(x) = 0.3218</m>, just as we have
said <m>y = f(x) =0.3218</m> in many instances before. Better yet would
be
<m>p = p(x) = 0.3218</m>, where the function and variable name are the
same
- one fewer thing to keep track of - and indicative of the measurement
of `pace'. Better <em>still</em> would be <m>p = p(t) = 0.3218t</m> were
the variable <m>t</m> could be a reminder of the measurement of
time.</p>

<p>Given a function there are really two things we might do
<ol>
<li><p>''plug in'' or evaluate with a known input value</p></li>
<li><p>set up and solve an equation for an unknown input value</p></li>
</ol>
The first of these tends to be a bit easier, the second can be much
harder (or in some cases impossible using or typical methods). </p>

<example xml:id="ex-aa">
<title> ... </title>
<statement>
<p>
In this case, given \text{any} value for <m>x</m> we can evaluate our
function <m>f(x) = (50+x)(50+x)</m>. For example, taking <m>x=6</m> we
write
<me>f(6) = (50+6)(50+6) = (56)(56) = 3136</me> and read ''<m>f</m> of
<m>6</m>
equals the quantity <m>50</m> plus <m>6</m> times the quantity <m>50</m>
plus
<m>6</m>.'' We plug in <m>6</m> for every instance of <m>x</m> on the
left-hand
side and the right hand side. We then use arithmetic operations to
calculate the value of the expression on the right-hand side. For
<m>x=0</m> we find <me>f(0) = (50+0)(50+0) = (50)(50) = 2500.</me>

</p>
</statement>
</example>

</section>
<p><!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... --></p>

<section xml:id="sec-Imagine">
<title>Imagine</title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>


<p><!-->\footnote{Imagine because we won't actually
devote too much time to this from an algebraic perspective.}">-->
One of the things we do with functions is set up and solve equations.
With this in mind we want to think about the mechanics of how we
actually solve the equations and what the solutions might mean. </p>

<p><!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... --></p>

</section>

<section xml:id="sec-Finding-your-roots">
<title> Finding your roots </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>Here `roots' refers to the zeros of a function <m>f(x)</m> or the
solutions
to the equation <m>f(x) = 0</m>. This is the set of all numbers
(associated
to a particular function) for which plugging in these values returns the
function value of zero. This can be most easily pictured as where the
graph of a function crosses the horizontal axis, though this isn't
always enough.</p>

<p>Thinking of a formula such as <m>y = 3x-7</m> we remind ourselves
that
there are two things we can do: `plug in' or solve an equation. Suppose
we know that <m>x = 4</m>, what can we do with this information? We can
evaluate right-hand side to say that when <m>x=4</m>, <me>y = 3(4)- 7 =
12 -
7 = 5</me>. Often when we talk about such formulas we think of them as
functions, for example, we might prefer to say <m>y = f(x) = 3x-7</m>.
This
really just says we generate a set of function values <m>y</m> that
correspond to the set of values <m>x</m>. In this case we might revisit
our
earlier problem with the notation that <m>f(4) = 3(4)-7 = 12</m>. We
have
`plugged in' the value <m>x=4</m> on each side of the function, on the
left
as a particular value of its argument and on the right in each position
that the argument occurs.</p>

<p>The other thing we can do given a formula or function is to calculate
an
unknown input from a known output. For example, we can answer the
question `what is <m>x</m> given that <m>y=17</m>?' Here we begin with
<me>17 =
3x-7</me> and solve for <m>x</m>. Specifically,
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
17 \amp = 3x-7\\
17+7 \amp = 3x-7 +7\\
24 \amp = 3x\\
x \amp = \sfrac{24}{3} = 8
\end{aligned}</me></p>

<p>Of these two tasks, plugging in or evaluating a function is typically
easier than setting up and solving an equation. That is not to say it is
easy, but typically easier than the other task.</p>

<subsection xml:id="sub-Square-roots-new-ideas">
<title> Square roots new ideas </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>
Way back when we discussed numbers, first the counting numbers, we saw
we could add and multiply and remain within that set of numbers.
Introducing subtraction required us to think about negative number (and
zero). Introducing division required us to think about rational numbers
and decimals (and soon after irrational numbers). Assuming we are
interested in calculating square roots of numbers in order to identify
what number can be multiplied twice to generate another, we have to
prepare for yet another complication. If we think of the square root
arising in the problem <me>(\underline{\quad})(\underline{\quad}) =
25</me>
we might recognize that a number that can be used in both blanks
simultaneously is <m>5</m>\footnote{It turns out that <m>-5</m> is a
valid
choice as well, since <m>(-5)(-5) = 25</m> also.}. Picturing this
multiplication problem we can think of other pairs of similarly related
numbers also,
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
({5})({5}) \amp= 25\\
({3})({3}) \amp= 9\\
({-1})({-1}) \amp= 1\\
({-3})({-3}) \amp = 9
\end{aligned}</me>
It turns out that there are two ways to generate the value <m>9</m> by
multiplication: of a <m>3</m> with itself and of a <m>-3</m> with
itself. We
write <me>\sqrt{9} = \pm3</me> in order to indicate both possibilities.
One
thing we might notice is that two positive factors yield in a positive
result, but so do two negative factors. A question is, ''what, if
anything, can we multiply against itself to generate a negative
result?''</p>

<p>The answer to this requires us to think of a new type of number, the
imaginary number. Here we say that the imaginary number <m>i</m> is a
number such that, <me>i\cdot i = i^2 = -1</me> or, from the reverse that
<me>\sqrt{-1} = i.</me> With this new concept we can build numbers
called
complex numbers that consist of our typical `real part' combined with a
term representing this new `imaginary part'. In general complex numbers
are of the form <m>a+bi</m>, where <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> come from our
usual sets
of numbers; they can be whole numbers, fractions or decimals, positives
or negatives.</p>

<p>For the moment we will (try to) accept this concept of a new kind of
number, just like we have for others along the way, and practice with it
in calculations. </p>

<example xml:id="complex-arithmetic">
<title> ... </title>
<statement>
<p>
Consider the real number <m>3</m> and four successive rounds of
multiplication by <m>i</m>. <me>\begin{aligned}[t]
(3)(i) \amp = 3i\\
(3i)(i) \amp = 3(i^2) = 3(-1) = -3\\
(-3)i \amp = -3i\\
(-3i)(i) \amp = (-3)(i^2) = (-3)(-1) = 3
\end{aligned}</me>
In this case multiplication by <m>i</m> flips a the real number <m>3</m>
back
and forth between real and imaginary. Four steps of multiplication sends
us back to our starting point. Notice, for example, that <m>i^4 =
(i^2)(i^2) = (-1)(-1) = 1</m>. In fact, no matter how we break up stages
of this calculation we see that <m>i^4 = 1</m>. So multiplying by
<m>i</m>
four times or by <m>i^4</m> one time both yield the same outcome.
</p>
</statement>
</example>


<example xml:id="complex-arithmetic-II">
<title> ... </title>
<statement>
<p>Consider the complex number <m>3+2i</m> and four successive rounds of
multiplication by <m>1+i</m>. <me>\begin{aligned}[t]
(3+2i)(1+i) \amp = 3\cdot1+3\cdot i+2i\cdot1 + 2i\cdot i\\
 \amp = 3 + 3i + 2i + 2(i^2)\\
 \amp = 3 + 3i + 2i + 2(-1)\\
 \amp = 3 + 5i - 2\\
 \amp 1 + 5i
\end{aligned}</me>
Now the point that used to be at coordinates <m>(3, 2)</m> has moved to
the
point at coordinates <m>(-1, 5)</m>. Convince yourself that one
additional
multiplication moves the point to <m>(-4,6)</m> corresponding to the
complex number <m>-4+6i</m>.</p>

<p>We visualize these steps in the image below, where <m>j</m> refers to
the
number of steps of multiplication.
<figure xml:id="figure-complex">

<image source = "./images/complex.png" width="85%" text="fingers for
counting">
              <description>Complex numbers.</description>
</image>
</figure>
<!-->\begin{center}\includegraphics[width=0.75\textwidth]{\figs/complex}
\end{
center">
--></p>
</statement>
</example>


<p>We can visualize this multiplication by constructing the complex
plane:
two perpendicular axes, one that describes real values and one that
describes imaginary values, which collectively describe all of the
complex numbers. Plotting these values in the complex plane and tracing
out the steps of multiplication, we can convince ourselves that each
step multiplication by <m>i</m> serves to rotate our number
counterclockwise around the origin of the graph. Here our numbers lie on
the axes (which are perpendicular to one another), so tracking the
rotations might be pictured a bit more easily than it can be in
general.</p>

<exercise xml:id="chall-complex-arithmetic">
<p>Complete four successive multiplications of <m>3+i</m> by <m>i</m>.
Do this
arithmetically and visually by using rotations about the origin. Did one
method come to you more easily than the other? Was one method more
interesting than the other?</p>
</exercise>

<exercise xml:id="chall-complex-arithmetic-II">
<p>Calculate each of the following.
<ol>
<li><p><m>(3+i)(1-2i)</m> <em>Hint: expand by FOIL.</em></p></li>
<li><p><m>(2-i)(3+2i)</m></p></li>
<li><p><m>(2-i) + (3+2i)</m> <em>Hint: combine real and complex
parts.</em></p></li>
<li><p><m>(1+i) - (5-2i)</m> <em>Hint: combine real and complex
parts.</em></p></li>
</ol>
</p>
</exercise>

<p>Complex numbers are typically first encountered in algebra when
working
with solutions to quadratic equations (but historically it seems that
they were first `invented' or realized when working with cubic
equations). Focusing on just the quadratic equations, analytical (i.e.,
on paper) solutions to <me>ax^2+bx+c=0</me> can generally be found by
factoring, completing the square, or applying the quadratic formula.
</p>

<p>We may remember the quadratic formula as <me>x = \frac{x = -b\pm
\sqrt{b^2
- 4ac}}{2a}</me> Without imaginary and complex numbers, we run into
trouble
when the term in the square root, called the `discriminant', is negative
because without them we could not take the square root. Indeed,
solutions are complex numbers if <me>b^2 -4ac \lt 0</me> this means we
can solve
the equation in terms of complex numbers, but that the graph will not
actually cross the horizontal axis as we are used to seeing happen.</p>

<p>Stepping aside, now that we have a need for square roots and an
appreciation of the connection to complex numbers, we will look at the
generation of fractals. The mathematical details of this will happen
behind the scenes, but the connection from complex numbers to fractals
is a strong one. After a brief discussion of fractals, we will return to
the world of real numbers, but look at the effects of repetition or
iteration on some more concrete problems.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="iteration-fractals">
<title>Repetition and a descent to fractals</title>

<introduction>
<p>Though the technical details are a bit much at the moment, there is a
strong connection between thinking about and working with complex
numbers and the generation of what are known mathematically as fractals.
</p>
</introduction>

In addition to being useful in their own way, when carefully visualized,
solutions to certain math problems generate neat pictures. Our first
fractal, Newton's map (see Fig. \ref{fig::nmap}), shows the `shooting
chart' for finding solutions to a particular mathematical problem that
arise by starting at different points on the `floor'.

<figure xml:id="figure-newtons88">

<image source = "./images/alpha8over8.png" width="85%" text="fingers for
counting">
              <description>A Newton's map fractal.</description>
</image>
</figure>
<!--\begin{figure}[h!">
\centering
\includegraphics[width=0.5\textwidth]{\figs/alpha8over8">
\caption{A classic representation of the Newton's Map fractal generated
using the program Processing.}\label{fig::nmap">
\end{figure">-->

<p>An analogy: If our goal is to keep track of basketball scoring, we
might
map all of the locations on one end of floor by a color that indicates
if a player that scored or missed from that location. We might even
change the intensity of the color by the number of makes or misses, or
the ratio of makes to misses.</p>

<figure xml:id="figure-newtons58">

<image source = "./images/alpha5over8.png" width="85%" text="fingers for
counting">
              <description>A Newton's map fractal.</description>
</image>
</figure>
<!--\begin{figure}[h!">
\centering
\begin{minipage}{0.48\textwidth">
\centering
\includegraphics[width=0.95\textwidth]{\figs/alpha5over8"></p>
-->
<figure xml:id="figure-newtons78">

<image source = "./images/alpha7over8.png" width="85%" text="fingers for
counting">
              <description>A Newton's map fractal.</description>
</image>
</figure>
<!-->
<p>\end{minipage">
\begin{minipage}{0.48\textwidth">
\centering
\includegraphics[width=0.95\textwidth]{\figs/alpha7over8">
\end{minipage"></p>
-->
<figure xml:id="figure-newtons98">

<image source = "./images/alpha9over8.png" width="85%" text="fingers for
counting">
              <description>A Newton's map fractal.</description>
</image>
</figure><!-->
<p>\begin{minipage}{0.48\textwidth">
\centering
\includegraphics[width=0.95\textwidth]{\figs/alpha9over8"></p>
-->
<figure xml:id="figure-newtons118">

<image source = "./images/alpha11over8.png" width="85%" text="fingers
for counting">
              <description>A Newton's map fractal.</description>
</image>
</figure>
<!-->
<p>\end{minipage">
\begin{minipage}{0.48\textwidth">
\centering
\includegraphics[width=0.95\textwidth]{\figs/alpha11over8">
\end{minipage"></p>

<p>\caption{Slight variations of the Newton's Map fractal generated
using
the program Processing.}\label{fig::nmap2">
\end{figure">-->
<!-->
%\paragraph{MORE PICTURES!} 
\subsubsection{Paper folding">
Other repetitive processes can generate interesting patterns as well.
Paper folding is on the cusp of art and science.
%\paragraph{PAPER FOLDING!">
%-->
%
<figure xml:id="figure-paper">

<image source = "./images/paper1.jpg" width="85%" text="fingers for
counting">
              <description>Paper folding.</description>
</image>
</figure>
<!--\begin{figure}[h!">
\centering
\begin{minipage}{0.48\textwidth">
\centering
\includegraphics[width=0.95\textwidth, angle=-90]{\figs/paper1"></p>
--><figure xml:id="figure-paper2">

<image source = "./images/paper2.jpg" width="85%" text="fingers for
counting">
              <description>Paper folding.</description>
</image>
</figure>
<!-->
<p>\end{minipage">
\begin{minipage}{0.48\textwidth">
\centering
\includegraphics[width=0.95\textwidth, angle=-90]{\figs/paper2">
\end{minipage"></p>
--><figure xml:id="figure-paper3">

<image source = "./images/paper3.jpg" width="85%" text="fingers for
counting">
              <description>Paper folding.</description>
</image>
</figure><!-->
<p>\begin{minipage}{0.48\textwidth">
\centering
\includegraphics[width=0.95\textwidth, angle=-90]{\figs/paper3"></p>

<p>\end{minipage">
\begin{minipage}{0.48\textwidth">
\centering
\includegraphics[width=0.95\textwidth, angle=-90]{\figs/paper4">
\end{minipage"></p>
--><figure xml:id="figure-paper4">

<image source = "./images/paper4.jpg" width="85%" text="fingers for
counting">
              <description>Paper folding.</description>
</image>
</figure>
<!-->
<p>\caption{Stages of paperfolding and cutting.}\label{fig::paper">
\end{figure">-->
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="sub-Repeated-approximation">
<title> Repeated approximation </title>

<p>
Having seen square roots arise in solving certain algebraic problems
(quadratic equations) or just certain arithmetic problems (square roots
of numbers), we will pause to think about how we might actually
calculate square roots of arbitrary numbers. We might know that because
<me>5\cdot5=25</me> that we can say <me>\sqrt{25} = 5</me> this is true
and
reflects the `principal square root'. But, we also have that
<me>(-5)\cdot(-5) = 25</me> and in general say <me>\sqrt{25} = \pm
5</me> to
indicate both ways of squaring a number to get <m>25</m>. Certain
numbers
we can take square roots of mentally by thinking about the repeated
factors that give rise to that number, but for others we are unable to
easily do so.</p>

<p>For example, what is the <m>\sqrt{3}</m>? At the start we might
observe
that <m>1\cdot1 = 1</m> and <m>2\cdot2=4</m>. We might believe that the
answer, the number that we multiply by itself to result in a value of
<m>3</m>, should be between <m>1</m> and <m>2</m>, perhaps even a little
closer
to <m>2</m> than to <m>1</m>. In a very surprising coincidence, the
mathematical technique, and even the more general approach, that lets us
approximate <m>\sqrt{3}</m> is actually the same as the one that
generated
our fractals. A technique called Newton's Method, when applied to this
problem, gives a mathematical rule for calculating a sequence of
approximations to a square root. The rule is given by <me>x_{n+1} =
\frac{1}{2}\left(x_n+\frac{\alpha}{x_n}\right)</me> where <m>x_n</m> is
the
<m>n^\text{th}</m> approximation to the square root. We imagine
<m>x_n</m> as
a sequence (or ordered list) of numbers starting at <m>n=0</m> with a
value
<m>x_0</m> and continuing as <m>n</m> grows by one at a time.</p>

<example xml:id="Approximating-sqrt-3">
<title>Approximating <m>\sqrt{3}</m></title>
<statement>
<p>Assuming that our <m>\alpha = 3</m> in our hopes of approximating
<m>\sqrt{3}</m>, we might start by guessing that <m>x_0 = 1</m> and
noticing
that the step after step <m>n=0</m> is step <m>n+1 = 0+1 = 1</m>, such
that
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
x_{0+1} \amp= \frac{1}{2}\left(x_0+\frac{3}{x_0}\right)\\
x_1 \amp= \frac{1}{2}\left(1+\frac{3}{1}\right)\\
 \amp= \frac{1}{2}\left(4\right)\\
 x_1 \amp = 2
\end{aligned}</me>
Now starting from <m>x_1 = 2</m> we take another step to calculate
<m>x_2</m>.
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
x_{1+1} \amp= \frac{1}{2}\left(x_1+\frac{3}{x_1}\right)\\
x_2 \amp= \frac{1}{2}\left(2+\frac{3}{2}\right)\\
 \amp= \frac{1}{2}\left(\frac{7}{2}\right)\\
 x_2 \amp = \frac{7}{4} = 1.75
\end{aligned}</me>
Repeating this some more (one last time in greater detail), 
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
x_3 \amp= \frac{1}{2}\left(\frac{7}{4}+\frac{3}{\sfrac{7}{4}}\right)\\
    \amp=
\frac{1}{2}\left(\frac{7}{4}+\frac{3}{1}\cdot\frac{4}{7}\right)\\
<!--text{replace <m>\div</m> with <m>\times</m> by reciprocal}\\-->
 \amp= \frac{1}{2}\left(\frac{7}{4}+\frac{12}{7}\right)\\
 \amp=
\frac{1}{2}\left(\frac{7}{7}\cdot\frac{7}{4}+\frac{4}{4}\cdot\frac{12}{7
}\right)\\
 \amp= \frac{1}{2}\left(\frac{49 + 48}{28}\right)\\
x_3 \amp= \frac{97}{56}\approx 1.732143
\end{aligned}</me></p>

<p>Continuing this it might help to visualize the results in a table.
Additionally it will no longer make sense to store exact fractions at
any step, since our computers are unable to do so anyway. This does save
us from having to do things like find common denominators, but does
require us to write down some fairly lengthy decimal numbers at
times.</p>

<table xml:id="tab-a-table">
<title>Application to approximate <m>\sqrt{3}</m> with Newton's Method.
After only 4 steps, the approximation is exact to 8 digits; after just
one more step, the first 16 digits are exact (correct digits are
bolded)</title>
<!-->\caption{Application to approximate <m>\sqrt{3}</m> with Newton's
Method.
After only 4 steps, the approximation is exact to 8 digits; after just
one more step, the first 16 digits are exact (correct digits are
underlined).}\label{tab::roots}\centering
-->
<tabular halign="center" left="minor" right="minor" top="minor"
bottom="minor">
<row><cell><m>n</m></cell><cell><m>x_n</m></cell></row>
<row><cell> 0 </cell> <cell> 1.0000000</cell></row>
<row><cell> 1 </cell> <cell> 2.0000000</cell></row>
<row><cell> 2 </cell> <cell> <alert>1.7</alert>500000</cell></row>
<row><cell> 3 </cell> <cell> <alert>1.732</alert>1429</cell></row>
<row><cell> 4 </cell> <cell> <alert>1.7320508</alert></cell></row>
<row><cell> 5 </cell> <cell> <alert>1.7320508</alert></cell></row>
</tabular>
</table>

<p>Our approximation of <m>\sqrt{3}</m> by <m>x_5\approx
1.732050807568877</m>
squares to <me>1.732050807568877^2=2.999999999999998</me> which is quite
impressive.</p>
</statement>
</example>


<exercise xml:id="ex-">
<p>We approximated <m>\sqrt{3}</m> to 8 correct digits in only 4 steps
starting from <m>x_0=1</m>. Do you think that the choice of <m>x_0</m>
matters? For each of <m>x_0</m> equal to each integer from <m>1</m> to
<m>10</m>
see how many steps it takes to reach 8 correct digits from that number.
Graph your results with points illustrating the number of steps required
(vertical) against the value of <m>x_0</m> (horizontal). This can be
done
by hand but will be a miserable amount of work, instead see if you can
use spreadsheet software to automate the calculation.
</p>
</exercise>

<exercise xml:id="ex-nnn">
<p>Try to approximate <m>\sqrt{7}</m> to 6 digits. What is a sensible
choice
of <m>x_0</m> and why?
</p>
</exercise>

</subsection>
<p><!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... --></p>

</section>

<section xml:id="sec-word-problems">
<title> Word problems </title>
<introduction> <p>
Word problems get a bad rap. 
<ul>
<li><p>What goes where?</p></li>
<li><p>What even matters?</p></li>
<li><p>Formatting numbers (e.g., is it <m>50\%</m> or
<m>0.50</m>?)</p></li>
<li><p>''I have to think!?!''</p></li>
<li><p>Show your work.</p></li>
<li><p>Problems are time-consuming.</p></li>
<li><p>Interpretation of answer often required.</p></li>
</ul>
But, work problems are an idealized version of most real-world problem
solving; in this case we know the course or book we are studying, the
unit or chapter, and the topic or section. So, it should be the case
that we know roughly <em>what</em> to do, even if we do not exactly know
<em>how</em> to do it mechanically. </p>

<p> ... </p> </introduction>



<subsection xml:id="sub-Life-is-a-word-problem">
<title> Life is a word problem </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>
Mathematical modeling is the art, and science, of writing and studying
your own word problems about interesting situations. We 1) take
real-world knowledge, 2) identify, often with the help of experts,
seemingly important facts and details, 3) develop a verbal or visual
`story' about what is happening, 4) translate the words and diagrams to
mathematical notation and formulas, and 5) study the math problem and
see what we have learned. This process is visualized in
Fig. \ref{fig::modeling}.</p>

<p>As we generate results, we compare those to the original mathematical
problem for consistency, then to the details of the biological problem.
If those first two stages are successful, we see if there is anything
that can be said about the real-world problem. If not, we revise our
assumptions, model, or analysis and try again. Here failure is expected
and provides a valuable chance to learn.</p>

<figure xml:id="figure-hard-problem">

<image source = "./images/hard_problem.png" width="85%" text="fingers
for counting">
              <description>Paper folding.</description>
</image>
</figure>

<p><!--\begin{figure}[h!">
\centering
\includegraphics[width=0.75\textwidth]{\figs/hard_problem">
\caption{Process of mathematical modeling.}\label{fig::modeling">
\end{figure">--></p>

<p>Unlike when we find ourselves solving word problems, here we do
<em>not</em> know the tool we are supposed to use. It requires a broad
training with a diverse set of techniques to pursue mathematical
modeling. Almost always one of these tools is a computer and an ability
to edit and write computer programs.</p>

<p>Mathematical modeling of infectious disease
Nearly every year we are faced with a newly emerged or reemerged
infectious pathogen somewhere around the planet. This is a math problem,
though one shared with experts from <em>many</em> other disciplines.
During the current coronavirus outbreak, caused by the pathogen known as
COVID19, mathematicians, some acting as mathematicians and others more
as statisticians, have featured prominently. Mathematicians (and
specialty-statisticians often referred to as epidemiologists) and others
are using the best available knowledge about the virus, its origin, its
transmission, and its effect on the infected, to try to understand the
pace of the current outbreak and to try to understand its future. </p>

<p>Many tools, most with mathematical and statistical roots, are coming
together to help interpret biological data (e.g., virus genetics,
patient responses) and population-level `public health' data (e.g.,
infections across geographic borders). Any time you see a graph of cases
plotted against time or deaths plotted against cases, or see the phrase
<m>R_0</m> (the British `naught' for <m>0</m>, so ''R-naught''), you are
seeing the results of mathematical reasoning or analysis. Specifically
the quantity <m>R_0</m> characterizes how infectious a pathogen is
expected
to be and gives the expected number of cases that one infectious person
might cause in a completely susceptible population. </p>

<p>The <em>simplest</em> example of a mathematical model, represented by
the diagram in <xref ref="fig-sir"/>, tracks the amount of a population
that is susceptible to infection and those that have the infection and
are infectious. The Greek symbols in the diagram denote
<em>parameters</em> and each symbol is acting as placeholder for a
particular number that is important to understanding how the possible
outbreak unfolds. Of the two numbers, <m>\beta</m> is slightly more
complicated and attempts to summarize how frequently individuals
interact and how likely it is that one of those interactions results in
transmission; <m>\gamma</m> is less complicated and reflects how long a
person remains infectious (i.e., it describes a `recovery rate').</p>

<figure xml:id="figure-compartment">

<image source = "./images/compartment.png" width="85%" text="fingers for
counting">
              <description>Compartment models.</description>
</image>
</figure>
<p><!--\begin{figure}[h!">
\centering
\includegraphics[width=0.5\textwidth]{\figs/compartment">
\caption{The simplest possible model diagram.}\label{fig::SI">
\end{figure">--></p>

<p><!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... --></p>

</subsection>
</section>

<section xml:id="sec-Modeling-with-functions">
<title> Modeling with functions </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>
If we are ultimately interested in modeling using mathematical
functions, we need to build up a catalog of mathematical functions.
Before we diversify too much, we will spend a but of time looking at
quadratic functions. Quadratic functions <me>f(x) = ax^2 + bx + c</me>
coupled with the quadratic formula <me>x =
\dfrac{-b\pm\sqrt{b^2-4ac}}{2a}</me> which gives the <m>x</m> values
that
solve <m>f(x) = 0</m>. What is surprising, perhaps, is just how often
and
in how many places the quadratic formula shows up as the lynchpin of so
many mathematical problems. Partly this is because so many problems are
ultimately studied in two dimensions. For example, we are used to
visualizing so many problems in the <m>xy</m>-plane.</p>

<p>As an example, consider a new problem in which we try to solve the
following <em>system</em> of equations,
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
\begin{cases}
2x+3y \amp = 7\\
5x+4y \amp = 9
\end{cases}
\end{aligned}</me></p>

<p>Specifically we are looking for the numbers <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>
that
<em>simultaneously</em> satisfy these equations. We could solve for one
variable from one equation and substitute into the other equation to
solve. Alternatively, we could solve each equation for <m>y</m>, graph,
and
look for the intersection. Proceeding in this direction,
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
2x+3y\amp=7\\
3y \amp = 7 - 2x\\
y \amp = -\dfrac{2}{3}x+\dfrac{7}{3}
\end{aligned}</me>
Similarly from the second equation,
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
5x+4y\amp=9\\
4y \amp = 9 - 5x\\
y \amp = -\dfrac{5}{4}x+\dfrac{9}{4}
\end{aligned}</me></p>

<p>We could start by graphing one of these, perhaps the second, whose
graph
is a straight line with slope of <m>m=-\sfrac{5}{4}</m> and
<m>y</m>-intercept of <m>b=\sfrac{9}{4}</m>. The graph of the line
starts
at a value of <m>\sfrac{9}{4}</m> on the <m>y</m>-axis, from there we go
down <m>5</m> units for every <m>5</m> units we move to the right (we
could
also picture going down <m>\sfrac{5}{4}</m> units for every <m>1</m> we
move to the right). We could superimpose a graph of the other and
identify the intersection, which corresponds to the solution to the
system of equations.</p>

<subsection xml:id="sub-Another-approach">
<title> Another approach </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>
Using some very different methods, we could rewrite the system 
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
\begin{cases}
2x+3y \amp = 7\\
5x+4y \amp = 9
\end{cases}
\end{aligned}</me>
in <em>matrix-vector</em> form as follows,
<me>\left(\begin{array}{cc}2 \amp 3 \\ 5 \amp
4\end{array}\right)\left(\begin{array}{c}x\\y\end{array}\right) =
\left(\begin{array}{c}7\\9\end{array}\right) </me>
To confirm that these are equal we perform <em>matrix-vector</em>
multiplication. To recover the first equation in the system we multiply
the entries in the first row by <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> and add between
each
step of multiplication. The result is equal to the top entry on the
right-hand side, the <m>7</m>. </p>

<p>With this square arrangement of numbers, the matrix, we enter the
field
of <em>linear algebra</em> (note: very closely associated with linear
algebra, especially in two dimensions, is the study of
<em>differential equations</em>). Linear algebra plays an essential role
in differential equations, and by association, so does the quadratic
formula.} which is broadly concerned with techniques for solving linear
systems of equations. Often we are less concerned with the solutions to
linear systems and we are more concerned with properties of the matrix
itself. One such property of the matrix actually requires us to
calculate solutions to an associated quadratic equation using the
quadratic formula. To say it again, there is a direct connection between
2D matrices (2 rows, 2 columns) and the quadratic formula. </p>
</subsection>

<p><!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... --></p>

<p><!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... --></p>

</section>

<section xml:id="sec-catalog-of-mathematical-functions">
<title> Catalog of mathematical functions </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<subsection xml:id="sub-Linear-functions">
<title> Linear-functions </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>Linear functions are those of the form <m>y = f(x) = mx+b</m>, we
call
<m>m</m> the slope and <m>b</m> the <m>y</m>-coordinate of the
<m>y</m>-intercept.
We can solve equations of evaluate functions. Graphs of linear functions
are straight lines. If the slope is positive, the line increases from
left to right (bigger <m>x</m> results in bigger <m>y</m>). If the slope
is
negative, the line decreases from left to right (bigger <m>x</m> results
in
smaller <m>y</m>). If the slope is zero, the line is flat or constant.



<figure xml:id="fig-linear-up">
	<caption>Graph of an increasing linear function.</caption>
		<image xml:id="image-linear-up" source="./images/linear_up.png"
width='50%'>
		</image>
</figure>


<figure xml:id="fig-linear-down">
	<caption>Graph of an decreasing linear function.</caption>
		<image xml:id="image-linear-down"
source="./images/linear_down.png"
width='50%'>
		</image>
</figure>

<figure xml:id="fig-linear-flat">
	<caption>Graph of an flat or constant linear function.</caption>
		<image xml:id="image-linear-flat"
source="./images/linear_flat.png"
width='50%'>
		</image>
</figure>

Linear functions are often used in regression to determine the slope and
intercept of a line that best summarize information in a scatterplot of
points.</p>

<example xml:id="Temperature-conversions">
<title> ... </title>
<statement>
<p>
A popular example of a linear function is <me>F = \dfrac{9}{5}C +
32</me>
which describes the temperature in degrees Fahrenheit as a function of
temperature in degrees Celsius. We might remember that the freezing
point of water is <m>32 {}^\circ\text{F}</m> and that the boiling point
is
<m>212 {}^\circ\text{F}</m>. We might be interested in representing
these
values in Celsius, and can pursue this by solving each of the following
equations for <m>C</m>,
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
32 \amp = \dfrac{9}{5}C+32\\
212 \amp = \dfrac{9}{5}C+32
\end{aligned}</me>
To solve each, we subtract <m>32</m> from each side and then multiply by
<m>\dfrac{5}{9}</m> to find that the freezing point of water os
<m>0 {}^\circ\text{C}</m> and the bioling point is
<m>100 {}^\circ\text{C}</m>. For example, 
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
32 \amp = \dfrac{9}{5}C+32\\
\cancel{32-32} \amp = \dfrac{9}{5}C+\cancel{32 - 32}\\
0 \amp = \dfrac{9}{5}C\\
\dfrac{5}{9}\cdot0 \amp = \cancel{\dfrac{5}{9}\cdot\dfrac{9}{5}}C\\
C \amp = 0
\end{aligned}</me>
</p>
</statement>
</example>

<exercise xml:id="chall-boiling-point">
Repeat the calculation to confirm the
boiling point of water in Celsius.
</exercise>

<example xml:id="Lime-rides">
<title> ... </title>
<statement>
<p>
Consider you are taking a \sout{taxi} Lime scooter ride. The
\sout{taxi">
Lime scooter charges a <m>$1.00</m> `unlock fee' then charges an
additional <m>$0.29</m> per minute. Write the linear function that
describes cost <m>c</m> as function of time spend riding <m>t</m>.
</p>
</statement>

<solution>
We can imagine in words that the cost is equal to the initial charge
plus the cost per minute multiplied by the number of minutes. This is
<me>c = c(t) = (\text{initial charge}) + (\text{cost per
minute})(\text{time spent riding})</me> or <me>c = c(t) = 1.00 +
0.29t</me> 
</solution>
</example>

<p>We can ask our usual sorts of questions about this function. For
example
''What if we made the poor decision to skip class and go on a 75-minute
camps joyride? How much would this cost?''</p>

<example xml:id="Joyride">
<title> ... </title>
<statement>
<p>''What if we made the poor decision to skip class and go on a
75-minute
campus joyride instead? How much would this cost?''
</p>
</statement>
<solution>
To answer this question, we evaluate <m>c(75)</m> to find the associated
cost.
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
c(75) \amp = 1.00 + 0.29(75)\\
\amp= 22.75
\end{aligned}</me>
</solution>
</example>

<p>Or, ''How long could I ride if I had a $5 credit?''</p>
<example xml:id="Account-credit">
<title> ... </title>
<statement>
<p>''How long could I ride if I had a $5 credit?''</p>
</statement>
<solution>
To answer this question, we solve <m>c(t) = 5</m> for the unknown value
of
<m>t</m>.
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
%5 \amp = c(t) \\
5 \amp= 1.00 + 0.29t\\
4.00 \amp= 0.29t\\
t\amp= \dfrac{4.00}{0.29} = 13.79\\
\end{aligned}</me>
</solution>

</example>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="sub-Quadratic-functions">
<title>Quadratic functions</title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>The simplest quadratic function is <m>f(x) = x^2</m>, whose graph is
a
`u'-shaped parabola (as opposed to `n'-shaped). This term is an example
of a power function, built from a variable raised to a number as a
power, <me>x^2 \text{ is of the form }
(\text{variable})^\text{number}.</me>
This form has important consequences for the properties of the formula
and its use in applications. With similar terms we can construct
polynomial functions such as, <me>g(x) = 3x^2+x^4</me> which are sums of
constants multiplied by powers of a variable.</p>

<p>Quadratic functions show up frequently in applications, for example
in
physics. We often study problems such as <m>s(t) = -4.9t^2 + 10t +
12</m>
where <m>s(t)</m> represents the height of an object thrown from a
height
of <m>12 \text{meters}</m> with an initial velocity of <m>10
\text{meters
per second}</m>. Because the number in front of <m>t^2</m> is negative,
the
graph of the corresponding parabola opens downward (as an upside down
`u'). There are a few ways that we can learn a little more about the
graph to determine the position of the curve within the <m>t-s</m> plane
(that is, in a plot of <m>s</m> against <m>t</m>).</p>

<p></p>

<p>
Notice that when <m>t = 0</m>, <m>s(0) = -4.9(0)^2 + 10(0) + 12 =
10</m>; the
graph of <m>s(t)</m> crosses the vertical axis at a value of <m>12</m>.
But
given the shape of the curve (an upside-down parabola), does the graph
intersect the point <m>(0, 12)</m> on its downstroke, at its vertex, or
on
its upstroke? There are a number of ways to answer this question
<ol>
<li><p>`cheat' and graph the formula using a computer (e.g., with Desmos
online, or even Google!) or graphing calculator</p></li>
<li><p>put the function in vertex form</p></li>
<li><p>apply methods of calculus</p></li>
<li><p>explore the formula using a hodge-podge of approaches</p></li>
</ol></p>

<p>We will take the last of these approaches. A question is (not
unrelated
to how we might reason about functions using calculus or even more
sophisticated approaches) is ''what does the graph look like when
<m>t</m>
is ''small''?'' Here we mean <m>t\approx0</m> to give an estimate of
what
we consider to be ''small'' values of <m>t</m>. Here thinking
numerically
about the relative contribution of each term gives some indication of
the value of the function in general. The values of each term and the
exact and approximate values of each function are given in
Table \ref{tab::position}.</p>


Sketches of possible graphs of an object in freefall that
starts from an initial height of <m>12 \text{meters}</m>. The graph must
pass through the point <m>(0, 12)</m> and be concave-down or `n`-shaped.
As
sketches, the axes are intentionally left without
numbers.

<figure xml:id="fig-quadratic-down">
	<caption>Graph of a possible quadratic position function for an
object in freefall.</caption>
		<image xml:id="image-quadratic-down"
source="./images/quadratic_down.png"
width='50%'>
		</image>
</figure>

<figure xml:id="fig-quadratic-top">
	<caption>Graph of a possible quadratic position function for an
object in freefall.</caption>
		<image xml:id="image-quadratic-top"
source="./images/quadratic_top.png"
width='50%'>
		</image>
</figure>


<figure xml:id="fig-quadratic-up">
	<caption>Graph of a possible quadratic position function for an
object in freefall.</caption>
		<image xml:id="image-quadratic-up"
source="./images/quadratic_up.png"
width='50%'>
		</image>
</figure>


<!--><tabular halign="center" left="minor" right="minor" top="minor"
bottom="minor">
<title>For values of <m>t</m> that are near and far from zero, the
contributions of each term in <m>s(t)</m> are given in the middle
columns.
For the first 4 rows, where <m>t</m> is `near' zero, we might imagine
ignoring the contribution of the quadratic term and notice that the
exact and approximate function values are still reasonably
close.</title>
<row><cell><m><m>t</m></m></cell><cell><m>-4.9t^2</m></cell></row>
<row><cell> 0 </cell> <cell> 1.0000000</cell></row>
<row><cell> 1 </cell> <cell> 2.0000000</cell></row>
<row><cell> 2 </cell> <cell> <alert>1.7</alert>500000</cell></row>
<row><cell> 3 </cell> <cell> <alert>1.732</alert>1429</cell></row>
<row><cell> 4 </cell> <cell> <alert>1.7320508</alert></cell></row>
<row><cell> 5 </cell> <cell> <alert>1.7320508</alert></cell></row>
</tabular>
</table>-->


<!--\begin{table}[h!]\centering
\caption{For values of <m>t</m> that are near and far from zero, the
contributions of each term in <m>s(t)</m> are given in the middle
columns.
For the first 4 rows, where <m>t</m> is `near' zero, we might imagine
ignoring the contribution of the quadratic term and notice that the
exact and approximate function values are still reasonably
close.}\label{tab::position">
\vspace{1em">
%\begin{tabular}{S[table-format=2.3]|S[table-format=3.3]S[table-format=3
%.3]S[table-format=3.3]||c|c">
\begin{tabular}{c|ccc||c|c">
{<m>t</m>} \amp {<m>-4.9t^2</m>} \amp {<m>10t</m>} \amp {<m>12</m>} \amp
{<m>s(t) \text{(exact)}</m>} \amp {<m>s(t) \text{(approx.)}</m>}\\
\hline\hline
\phantom{1}0.001 \amp \phantom{00}-0.0000049 \amp \phantom{10}0.010 \amp
12.0 \amp
\phantom{00}12.0099 \amp \phantom{-0}12.01\\
\phantom{1}0.010 \amp \phantom{00}-0.0004900 \amp \phantom{10}0.100 \amp
12.0 \amp
\phantom{00}12.0995 \amp \phantom{-0}12.10\\
\phantom{1}0.100 \amp \phantom{00}-0.0490000 \amp \phantom{10}1.000 \amp
12.0 \amp
\phantom{00}12.9510 \amp \phantom{-0}13.00\\
\phantom{0}1.000 \amp \phantom{00}-4.9000000 \amp \phantom{0}10.000 \amp
12.0 \amp
\phantom{00}17.1\phantom{000} \amp\phantom{-0}22.00\\
10.000 \amp -490.0000000 \amp 100.000 \amp 12.0 \amp -378.0\phantom{000}
\amp -378.00
\end{tabular">
\end{table-->

<p>The results in Tab. XX (are not shown because they weren't
particularly helpful) suggests that the height is
initially increasing (by the exact values, or by the approximation). The
approximation, neglecting the contribution of the <m>t^2</m> term for
small
values of <m>t</m> suggests that the position initially increases in an
approximately linear fashion. At some point though, the quadratic term
starts to play a role. It seems quite strange that <m>s(10) = -378</m>,
this would suggest that the object is <m>378 \text{meters}</m> below the
surface of the ground. It should be the case that at some point prior,
the model stops making sense. In fact, we could use the quadratic
formula to determine when the object lands. Solving for <m>s(t) = 0</m>
gives the value(s) of time <m>t</m> for which the height from the ground
is
zero.
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
x \amp= \dfrac{-10\pm\sqrt{10^2 - 4(-4.9)(12)}}{2(-4.9)}\\
\amp = \dfrac{-10\pm\sqrt{335.2}}{-9.8}\\
x \amp = -0.847,\,\,2.889\\
\end{aligned}</me>
The negative value does not make as much sense because this suggests
that the object was on the ground \text{before} we threw it upwards - we
are only really concerned with the future after <m>t=0</m>. From our
hodge-podge analysis we have that the object starts from a height of
<m>12 \text{meters}</m>, increases approximately linearly for a brief
span,
and with the shape of a parabola eventually comes back down and lands at
<m>t\approx2.899</m>. The mathematical equation is valid for all time,
but
after this the equation as a mathematical object of the flight of the
object stops making sense.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="sub-Polynomials">
<title>Polynomials</title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>As mentioned in the previous section, <me>g(x) = 3x^2+x^4</me> is an
example
of a polynomial. This category can be written as a sum of multiples of
powers of a variable, for example <me>p_n(x) = \sum_{i=0}^n a_i x_i</me>
where in the example for <m>g(x)</m> we would have <m>n=4</m> with
<m>a_0 = a_1
= a_3 = 0</m>, and <m>a_2 = 3</m> and <m>a_4 = 1</m>. In summation form,
<me>g(x)
= \sum_{i=0}^4 a_i x^i = 0x^0 + 0x^1 + 3x^2 + 0x^3 + 1x^4 = 3x^2 +
x^4</me></p>

<p>
Applications of polynomials are numerous, this stems partly from the
fact that they are `easy' to evaluate. The word `easy' refers to the
fact that there might be many, many terms to keep track of, but that it
only requires elementary operations of addition or subtraction and
multiplication. As a consequence, polynomials play an important role in
how we evaluate most functions using calculators or computers.</p>

<p>As a few examples of polynomials, consider <m>f(x) = x^3</m> and
<m>g(x) =
x^3-x</m>. In the second of these, the subtraction of <m>x</m> has a
dramatic
impact on the graph (see <xref ref="fig-cubic-factored"/>). </p>

<figure xml:id="fig-cubic-simple">
	<caption>The graph of <m>f(x) = x^3</m> crosses the horizontal axis
only once.</caption>
		<image xml:id="image-cubic-simple"
source="./images/cubic_simple.png" width='50%'>
		</image>
</figure>


<figure xml:id="fig-cubic-factored">
	<caption>The graph of <m>g(x) = x^3-x</m> crosses the horizontal
axis at three distinct
values.</caption>
		<image xml:id="image-cubic-factored"
source="./images/cubic_factored.png" width='50%'>
		</image>
</figure>

<p>Side-by-side, the graph of <m>f(x) = x^3</m> is relatively less
interesting
than that of <m>g(x) = x^3 - x</m>. Given a sketch, it appears that
<m>x^3</m>
only has one zero, while <m>x^3-x</m> has three zeroes. In general it
isn't
as easy to use something like the quadratic formula for solutions to
polynomial equations with higher powers. Here however, we get a bit
lucky and can do some factoring of <m>x^3-x</m>. It turns out that in
solving this, we can write <me>x(x^2-1)= 0 </me> as a first step. To
solve
this equation either factor can be zero. From the first factor we have
<m>x=0</m>, additionally from the second we can solve <m>x^2-1=0</m> to
find
the locations of other solutions. We have three strategies, guessing
solutions, attempting to factor, or applying the quadratic formula (the
second equation is a quadratic after all).</p>

<p>If we factor, we might notice this as a difference of squares
(<m>x^2</m>
and <m>1</m> can each be written as squares, of <m>x</m> and <m>1</m>,
respectively). We have <me>x^2-1 = (x+1)(x-1)</me> From here we set each
factor to zero to find the <m>x</m> values that solve this equation and
the
original equation. The value are <m>x = -1</m> and <m>x=1</m>, or
<m>x=\pm 1</m>.
Alternatively we could apply the quadratic formula to this quadratic
with <m>a = 1</m>, <m>b=0</m>, and <m>c=-1</m>
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
x \amp= \dfrac{-0\pm\sqrt{0^2 - 4(1)(-1)}}{2(1)}\\
\amp = \dfrac{\pm\sqrt{4}}{2}\\
x \amp = \pm 1\\
\end{aligned}</me>
Taking a peek back at the original formula for <m>g(x) = x^3-x</m> we
might
notice we could have originally factored this as <m>g(x) =
x(x+1)(x-1)</m>
(we can multiply this out to check that it agrees with the original
formula). The factored form illustrates that for <m>g(x) = 0</m> any one
of
the factors can be zero, each of which agrees with our solutions
above.</p>
</subsection>


<subsection xml:id="sub-Power-functions">
<title> Power functions </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>
In some sense power functions are simpler than polynomials, they only
contain a single term. But often that term is less familiar than those
that occur in polynomials. For example, we might be interested in
<m>f(x)
= x^{0.5}</m> or <m>g(x) = x^{0.75}</m> where are non-integer powers of
the
variable of interest. These functions take on very different shapes and
are useful in a variety of situations. The square root function is an
example of a power function <m>\sqrt{x} = x^{0.5}</m> which has the
shape
of a `sideways parabola', <m>x^1 = x</m> is another (a straight line),
<m>x^2</m> which has the shape of a normal parabola, as well as <m>x</m>
raised to any other power. We can also put a constant factor out in
front, for example <me>f(x) = 1.4x^{0.24}</me></p>



<figure xml:id="fig-power">
	<caption>Graphs of three power functions, <m>f(x) = \sqrt{x}</m>
(red, solid),  <m>g(x) = x</m> (black, dashed),  <m>h(x) = x^2</m>
(blue, dotted).</caption>
		<image xml:id="image-power" source="./images/power_funs.png"
width='50%'>
		</image>
</figure>

<p>Power functions are often used as formulas to represent simple
nonlinear
patterns.  Three classic examples are species-area accumulation curves,
the skull length-backbone length relationship in fossil fish, and the
connection between the metabolism-body mass relationship of mammals and
the accidental overdoes of an elephant with LSD.</p>
</subsection>


<subsection xml:id="sub-Species-area-curves">
<title>Species-area curves </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>
<p><me>S = ma^b</me></p>

</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="sub-Skull-backbone-curve">
<title> Skull-backbone curve </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>
<p><me>S = 1.162B^{0.993}</me></p>

</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="sub-Kleibers-Law-curve">
<title> Kleiber's Law curve </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>In terms of energy use (i.e., metabolism), a mouse must eat half of
its
body mass per day in order to survive, an elephant much less.  In fact,
the energy metabolism, <m>E</m>, of an animal as a function of its body
mass, <m>M</m>, is described by <me>E = (\#)M^{0.75}</me> This
relationship
holds across a remarkable range of organism sizes and was originally
built by trying to understand the relationship between the surface area
(amount of skin) and volume (amount within the skin).</p>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="sub-Rational-functions">
<title> Rational functions </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>Rational functions are any ratios of two separate polynomials. For
example, <me>r(x) = \dfrac{-4.9x^2+10x+12}{x^3-x}</me> is a rational
function. These functions can take on a variety of interesting and
useful shapes as graphs.</p>

<figure xml:id="fig-rats">
	<caption>Graphs of two rational functions, <m>f(x) =
\dfrac{x}{1+x}</m> (red, solid) and <m>g(x) = \dfrac{x}{1+x^2}</m>
(black, dashed).</caption>
		<image xml:id="image-rats" source="./images/rats.png"
width='50%'>
		</image>
</figure>

</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="sub-Exponentials-and-Logarithms">
<title> Exponentials and Logarithms </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>Most importantly is that we recognize that exponential functions are
of the form
<me>(\text{number})^\text{variable}</me> in contrast to power functions
which
are of the form <me>(\text{variable})^\text{number}</me> Exponential
functions (see Fig. \ref{fig::exp}) seem to be frequently confused with
quadratic functions (see Fig. \ref{fig::power}).  Looking at the graphs
however, the quadratic has a symmetry (for <m>x^2</m> a fold along the
vertical axis) that the exponentials lack.
</p>

<figure xml:id="fig-exps">
	<caption>The coincidence of exponentials written in arbitrary bases
and
base-<m>e</m>. Left: Graphs of three exponential functions, each of the
form <m>(\text{number})^\text{variable}</m>. Right: Same exponential
functions as graphed in at left, but now written in terms of
base-<m>e</m>
exponentials.</caption>
		<image xml:id="image-exps" source="./images/exps.png"
width='100%'>
		</image>
</figure>


<p>Exponential decay functions are plotted in Figure
\ref{fig::expdecay}.</p>

<figure xml:id="fig-exp-decay">
	<caption>The coincidence of exponential decay functions written in
arbitrary bases and
base-<m>e</m>. Left: Graphs of three exponential decay functions, each
of the
form <m>(\text{number})^\text{variable}</m>. Right: Same exponential
decay 
functions as graphed in at left, but now written in terms of
base-<m>e</m>
exponentials.</caption>
		<image xml:id="image-exp-decay" source="./images/exp_decays.png"
width='100%'>
		</image>
</figure>


<p><!--\begin{figure}[h!]\centering</p>

<p>\begin{minipage}{0.48\textwidth"></p>

<p>\begin{tikzpicture}[yscale=1.5, xscale=1.5">
 \draw[step=0.5, very thin, color=gray] (-2.1,-0.1) grid (2.1, 3.1);
 \draw[->] (-2.1,0) __ (2.1,0) node[below left] {$x$};
 \draw[->] (0,-0.1) __ (0,3.1) node[above] {$y$};
 \draw[color=red, very thick, domain=-0.49:2.0, <->] plot[id=fastdecay">
function{0.1**x)} node[right] {$0.1^{x}$};
 \draw[color=blue, very thick, domain=-1.13:2.0, <->] plot[id=edecay">
function{exp(-x)} node[above right] {$0.36^x$};
 \draw[color=black, very thick, domain=-2.1:2.0, <->]
plot[id=slowdecay">
function{0.8**x} node[above right] {$0.8^x$};
\end{tikzpicture"></p>

<p>\end{minipage">
\begin{minipage}{0.48\textwidth"></p>

<p>\begin{tikzpicture}[yscale=1.5, xscale=1.5">
 \draw[step=0.5, very thin, color=gray] (-2.1,-0.1) grid (2.1, 3.1);
 \draw[->] (-2.1,0) __ (2.1,0) node[below left] {$x$};
 \draw[->] (0,-0.1) __ (0,3.1) node[above] {$y$};
 \draw[color=red, very thick, domain=-0.49:2.0, <->] plot[id=fastdecay">
function{exp(-2.3*x)} node[right] {$e^{-2.3x}$};
 \draw[color=blue, very thick, domain=-1.13:2.0, <->] plot[id=edecay">
function{exp(-x)} node[above right] {$e^{-x}$};
 \draw[color=black, very thick, domain=-2.1:2.0, <->]
plot[id=slowdecay">
function{exp(-0.22*x)} node[above right] {$e^{-0.22x}$};
\end{tikzpicture">
\end{minipage"></p>

<p>\caption{The coincidence of exponentials written in arbitrary bases
and
base-<m>e</m>. Left: Graphs of three exponential functions, each of the
form <m>(\text{number})^\text{variable}</m>. Right: Same exponential
functions as graphed on the left, but now written in terms of
base-<m>e</m>
exponentials.}\label{fig::expdecay">
\end{figure">--></p>


<example xml:id="Paper-folding">
<title> ... </title>
<statement>
<p>
Exponential functions show up in a variety of places, such as population
growth.  A return to paperfolding provides a somewhat surprising
connection to exponential functions.  Taking the thickness of a piece of
paper after fold number <m>n</m> to be represented by <m>t_n</m>, we can
track
the thickness of the paper as we fold.  For example, <me>t_1 = 2t_0 =
2(0.01) = 0.02</me> and <me>t_2 = 2t_1 = 2(0.02) = 0.04</me> After
<m>n</m> folds
we actually have doubled <m>n</m> times, and can write <me>t_n =
2^n(t_0)</me>
This is precisely exponential growth, as illustrated in
Table \ref{tab::paper}.  Since the width is divided in half after each
fold, we can also calculate the remaining width of paper in a similar
manner.
<!-->\begin{table">
\centering
\caption{Thickness and width of standard copy paper after <m>n</m>
folds.}\label{tab::paper"></p>

<p>\begin{tabular}{ccc">
number of folds, <m>n</m> \amp thickness of paper,  <m>t_n
(\text{mm})</m> \amp
width of paper (mm)\\
\hline\hline
0 \amp  0.01 \amp 27.94\\
1 \amp 0.02 \amp 13.97\\
2 \amp 0.04 \amp 6.99\\
3 \amp 0.08 \amp 3.49\\
4 \amp 0.16 \amp 1.75\\
5 \amp 0.32 \amp 0.87\\
6 \amp 0.64 \amp 0.44\\
7 \amp 1.28 \amp 0.22\\
8 \amp 2.56 \amp 0.11
\end{tabular">
\end{table--></p>

<p>An easily overlooked complication lies in Table \ref{tab::paper}: by
the
sixth fold, the paper is actually thicker than it is wide. There is no
longer enough paper to fold!  <em>Assuming</em> that we could fold the
paper 100 times, it would be <m>1.268\times10^{28} \text{mm}</m> (or
<m>1.268\times10^{22} \text{kilometers}</m>) thick!  These results, are
illustrated in Fig. \ref{fig::paper_exp}.  The diameter of the earth is
<m>1.2742\times10^4 \text{kilometers}</m>, so this result is shocking if
not almost incomprehensible.</p>

<figure xml:id="figure-exp-folds">

<image source = "./images/exp_folds.pdf" width="85%" text="fingers for
counting">
</image>
</figure>
<p><!--\begin{figure}\centering
\includegraphics[width=0.45\textwidth]{\figs/exp_folds">
\caption{Theoretical results showing the thickness and width (in mm) as
a piece of standard printer paper is repeatedly
folded.}\label{fig::paper_exp">
\end{figure">-->
</p>
</statement>
</example>

<p>As a follow-up to exponential functions are logarithmic functions. 
Recall that we can think of the logarithm of some number of interest as
the power to which we raise another number to get that number of
interest. For example, in terms of powers of <m>10</m>, <me>10^4 =
10,000 \text{can be expressed as} \log_{10}(10,000) = 4</me> Each of
these
translates to the understanding that <m>4</m> factors of <m>10</m> is
ten
thousand or <m>10</m> to the fourth power is <m>10,000</m>.  Similarly
the
relationship <me>2^4 = 16 \text{can be expressed as} \log_2(16) =
4</me></p>

<p>In addition to thinking of single calculations of logarithms of
numbers,
we can talk about logarithm <em>functions</em>.  We plot the graph of
the natural logarithm in Fig. \ref{fig::ln}.  The natural logarithm
<m>\ln(x)</m> gives the exponent to to which we raise <m>e</m> to arrive
at
the argument of the natural logarithm.</p>

<p><!--\begin{figure}[h!]\centering</p>

<p>\begin{tikzpicture}[yscale=1.5, xscale=1.5">
 \draw[step=0.5, very thin, color=gray] (-2.1,-2.1) grid (2.1, 2.1);
 \draw[->] (-2.1,0) __ (2.1,0) node[ right] {$x$};
 \draw[->] (0,-2.1) __ (0, 2.1) node[above] {$y$};
 \draw[color=blue, very thick, domain=-2.1:0.6931, <->] plot[id=e2">
function{exp(x)} node[above ] {$e^x$};
 \draw[color=black, thick, dashed, domain=-2:2, <->] plot[id=x">
function{x} node[above right] {$y=x$};
 \draw[color=red, very thick, domain=0.122:2.0, <->] plot[id=ln">
function{log(x)} node[ right] {$\ln(x)$};
\end{tikzpicture">
\caption{Reflection of <m>e^x</m> across <m>y = x</m> to give the
inverse,
<m>\ln(x)</m>.}\label{fig::ln">
\end{figure">--></p>

</subsection>

<p>
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
</p>
</section>

<section xml:id="sec-Applications-of-functions">
<title> Applications of functions </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<subsection xml:id="sub-Mathematical-modeling-reprise">
<title> Mathematical-modeling-reprise </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>
When modeling spread of something infectious (a pathogen, a rumor, a
behavior) we break a population into relevant groups.  One of the
simplest breakdowns is into groups of 
<ol>
<li><p>susceptible (these are the `healthy' people)</p></li>
<li><p>infectious</p></li>
<li><p>recovered</p></li>
</ol>
There are some subtleties here that I will mention, but not spend any
more time on.  The name of the group `infectious' suggests that these
individuals are not only <em>infected</em>, but are also capable of
transmitting their infection to others. The `recovered' group is
sometimes called `removed' to indicate the group of individuals that are
<em>removed</em> from the process of infection either by natural
recovery or death.</p>

<p>The way infection is modeled is by a system of <em>differential
equations</em> which describe how the number of individuals within each
population is assumed to change over time, as individuals flow between
groups.  A diagram of the possible transitions is given in
<xref ref="fig-sir-diagram"/>.</p>

<figure xml:id="fig-sir-diagram">
<caption>One of the simpler versions of an SIR <em>compartment</em>
model.</caption>
<image source = "./images/sir.png" width="50%">
</image>
<!--><latex-image>
\begin{tikzpicture}[node distance=2.5cm,auto,>=latex]
    \node [draw, minimum size=1cm, fill=blue] (a)
{\textcolor{white}{\(\mathbf S\)}};
    \node [draw, minimum size=1cm, fill=red] (b) [right of=a]
{\textcolor{white}{\(\mathbf I\)}};
    \node [draw, minimum size=1cm, fill=black] (c) [right of=b]
{\textcolor{white}{\(\mathbf R\)}};
    \node (d) [above right of = b] {};
    \path[->, thick] (a) edge node {\small Infection} (b);
    \path[->, thick] (b) edge node {\small Recovery} (c);
    \path[->, thick] (b) edge [] node {\small Death} (d);
    \path[->, bend right, out=90, in=90, thick] (c) edge node {\small
Loss of immunity} (a);
\end{tikzpicture}
                </latex-image>
            </image>-->
        </figure>


<p>When we try to translate these assumptions into a mathematical model
we
begin with
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
\text{change in susceptible} \amp = -\text{(people getting sick)} +
\text{(people losing imunity)}\\
\text{change in infectious} \amp = + \text{(people getting sick)} -
\text{(people recovering)} - \text{(people dying from infection)}\\
\text{change in recovered} \amp = + \text{(people recovering)} -
\text{(people losing immunity)}
\end{aligned}</me>
We translate this to more mathematical language involving some calculus
as follows
<me>\begin{aligned}[t]
\dfrac{dS}{dt}\amp = -\beta S I + \rho R\\
\dfrac{dI}{dt} \amp =  \beta S I - \gamma I - \delta I\\
\dfrac{dR}{dt} \amp = \gamma I - \rho R
\end{aligned}</me>
The specific equations are not of great importance here, but you could
hopefully imagine that the number of new infections depends on the
number that are susceptible to infection (<m>S</m>) and the number that
can
transmit infection (<m>I</m>), so in some way the amount of new
infections
combines those two values.  Similarly, the number of individuals that
recover should depend on the amount that are infectious and the number
of individuals that lose immunity should depend on the number that have
recovered.  </p>

<p>The Greek letters are called `parameters'; these are symbols used to
represent various numbers like the transmission parameter <m>\beta</m>
or
the recovery rate <m>\gamma</m> (see Table \ref{tab::epi}).  Sometimes
it
is easier to write and study the model generically without having to
worry about the precise decimal values that go in these positions, so we
use the Greek letters as placeholders. This is similar to how we use the
formula <m>y=mx+b</m> to describe a linear function between variables
<m>y</m>
and <m>x</m>.  Whether or not we have acknowledged this before, <m>m</m>
and
<m>b</m> are parameters of the linear formula (`slope' and
`<m>y</m>-intercept', respectively). Changes to these numbers might
change
the appearance, but do not change the fundamental nature of the
relationship between <m>y</m> and <m>x</m>.


<!--\begin{table}[h!]\centering
\caption{Connections between real-world features of disease and
mathematical parameters.}\label{tab::epi">
\begin{tabular}{cc">
Factor \amp Related parameter\\
\hline\hline
Transmission parameter \amp <m>\beta</m>\\
Average time sick \amp <m>\gamma</m>\\w
Percent infections resulting in death \amp <m>\delta</m>\\
Duration of immunity \amp <m>\rho</m>\\
\hline
\end{tabular}\end{table-->"></p>

</subsection>


<subsection xml:id="sub-dots">
<title> ... </title>
<introduction> <p> ... </p> </introduction>

<p>Then a week went by as we experienced the early stages of a pandemic.

Models have been used as decision-making tools worldwide. Models have
been both fairly and unfairly criticized.  Graphs, tables, jargon have
showed up <em>everywhere</em>.</p>

<p><!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... -->
<!-- ....... .............. .............. ....... --></p>

</subsection>
</section>
</chapter>